<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the government of the thoughts by George Tullie ...</title>
            <author>Tullie, George, 1652?-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1827</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12075936</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12075936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 583:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the government of the thoughts by George Tullie ...</title>
                  <author>Tullie, George, 1652?-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The government of the thoughts.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Philosophy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53603:1"/>
            <p> A DISCOURSE OF THE Government OF THE THOUGHTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>GEORGE TULLIE.</hi> Sub-Dean of <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell.</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> 
               <abbr>MDCXCIV</abbr>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:53603:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Imprimatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 17. 1693.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Geor. Royſe</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. in Chriſto Patri ac Dom. Dom. <hi>Johanni</hi> Archiep. Cantuar. à ſacris Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53603:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE Moſt Reverend Father in God</hi> JOHN <hi>By Divine Providence Lord Arch-Biſhop of</hi> York, <hi>His Grace, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of</hi> England <hi>and Metroplitan.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT I take the liberty to Prefix ſo Great a Name to ſo ſmall a Treatiſe, only the
<pb facs="tcp:53603:3"/> Dignity of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, indeed makes ſome Compenſation for the defects and meanneſs of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, for the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is Truly Great and Noble in it ſelf, and what would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a much abler Pen, more leiſure for Abſtractions, a more Philoſophical Genius, and both a
<pb facs="tcp:53603:3"/> wider compaſs, and a cloſſer collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Thought, than any I can pretend to. Thus much however may be ſaid, that a ſenſe of that Edification, which ought always to be the cheif aim and Deſign of the Pulpit, which firſt gave Birth to this Diſcourſe, obliged
<pb facs="tcp:53603:4"/> me to write as fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally as the Subject would well admit of. Such as it is, My Lord, my Relation to the Church of <hi>York,</hi> the Juſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem one has for the Concurrence of ſo many excellent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications in one Perſon, and my particular obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:53603:4"/> to your Grace makes this publick Acknowledgment of them a Juſt Debt from,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt Dutiful and Obliged Servant. GEORGE TULLIE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:53603:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THO I have no great opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Prefaces, to ſmall Tracts eſpecially, that ſeem not to require any <hi>Prolegomena,</hi> and ſo conſequently deſign'd none, yet, ſince the printing This off, I find my ſelf under a ſort of obligation to ſay ſomething that way, having been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by ſome Friends that there was a Treatiſe lately publiſh'd (which has ſince come to my hands) with the
<pb facs="tcp:53603:5"/> ſame Title I deſign'd for mine, and with a great name annex'd to it, and that both the Book, and the <hi>Vanity</hi> (as they thought it) of the Title page paſs'd for mine with thoſe that did not know me. From which impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation the publiſhing of this will, I hope, ſufficiently clear me.</p>
            <p>As to the Tract it ſelf I ſhall make no other reflexion on it, than that it were indeed to be wiſh'd that That excellent perſon, whoſe name the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is pleas'd to make uſe of, had carried on his Meditations from <hi>The Government of the Tongue,</hi> to the Springs and Wheels of all its mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thoſe <hi>Thoughts</hi> that ſet it a going; for then we might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected a juſt diſcourſe indeed upon the Argument.</p>
            <p>I have little more to add, but that I am ſenſible the ſubject I have here undertaken might be managed after a
<pb facs="tcp:53603:6"/> much different manner from what it is by me, and that without running out either into the wide field of Logic or the Paſſions, which are diſtinct Arguments, both in themſelves, and from what I here intended.</p>
            <p>A Man who can turn his eyes vigorouſly inward, and read the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and myſterious part of himſelf, might, no doubt, make ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections thereupon, not unworthy the obſervation of the thinking World; as, that in our moſt abſtracted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearches after Truth, our notices of things are fetch'd more from extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and accidental hints than a juſt and <hi>regular</hi> inquiry, and a Man often <hi>falls upon</hi> a lucky thought as caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Gunpowder</hi> were invented; that if the motion of our Thoughts in compoſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> like that of the Sun, be both quick and bright too, that yet ſomthing of
<pb facs="tcp:53603:6"/> 
               <hi>Earth,</hi> as the objects of ſenſe, a fume or vapour in the head often interpoſes betwixt us and the <hi>Sun-ſhine</hi> we enjoyed, and <hi>Eclipſes</hi> the expected diſcovery; that ſometimes a ſudden <hi>flaſh</hi> of Thought breaks in upon us, but either ſo faintly bright, that it but juſt <hi>gildes</hi> our Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and then flies off, or ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully, that it <hi>dazles</hi> and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powers our Faculties, that we cannot retain it, as Meats of too high a Taſte are not eaſily digeſted by a weak Stomach; that if our Thoughts run <hi>turbid</hi> and <hi>lutulent,</hi> as the <hi>dregs</hi> and <hi>ſediments</hi> of Mortality will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten make them do, that then they riſe not up to the heighth of their Subject, if quick and nimble, that they ſeldom prove ſolid and weighty, as the ſame ſtream is rarely rapid and deep too; that the Poſition of a Chain of Thoughts may be eaſilier banter'd
<pb facs="tcp:53603:7"/> than confuted, and that their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion is by no means ſo fortuitous a thing as unobſerving men are apt to apprehend it. He might ſhew par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and at large, how the prejudices of Education, Intereſt, Paſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pervert the Sentence of the Underſtanding, when it ſits upon its Object; that hence princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally derive thoſe different ſentiments of things and perſons, that ſo much imbroil the World; and that were it not for theſe bribes that corrupt our Thoughts, all Mankind would <hi>think</hi> a-like here, as 'tis certain they will do in each different ſtate hereafter, ſince Truth in every thing is ſtill the ſame, and like its Great Author, can be but one, a ſtreight line that admits of none but it ſelf betwixt the ſame indiviſible points, and that 'tis therefore in a conſiderable meaſure the <hi>obliquity</hi> of mens Wills and
<pb facs="tcp:53603:7"/> Affections that hinder their thoughts from running <hi>parallel</hi> with it and one another.</p>
            <p>Thus a man by obſerving the <hi>working</hi> of his Thoughts upon all Occaſions, whether of ſpeculation or practice, might furniſh the World with ſuch Remarks as would carry both Pleaſure and Profit in them, and let us more and more into the knowledge of the <hi>terra incognita</hi> of our own leſſer World, ſhew us both <hi>how</hi> we <hi>think,</hi> and how we might improve the mighty Talent. And herein the <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was admirably great: He read him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and therein all Mankind, in their true light and proper colours; for one man, ſtript to his reaſon and the due uſe of his faculties, is but the counterpart of another. His Logic was the pure reſult of his own Obſervations upon the working of
<pb facs="tcp:53603:8"/> his Thoughts and the proceeds of his Reaſon: for Logic does not teach us to argue, Nature did that before it, but reduces our arguings into rules and methods, and ſhews us <hi>how</hi> we do it.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reflections I have only briefly and haſtily huddled together, that if they chance to <hi>fall in</hi> with any happy and obſerving Genius, they may ſet it on work, and be the fortunate occaſion of more perfect and conſummate productions in this kind, and then I ſhould think this lame and imperfect Eſſay infinitely better beſtow'd than otherwiſe 'tis like to be; for I am ſo ſenſible of its Imperfections, that I could bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily wiſh it in my hands again. But 'tis now out of my own power, and ſo I muſt be content to lie at the mercy of the Reader for venturing with ſo ſmall a force of Thought on
<pb facs="tcp:53603:8"/> ſo great and noble an Argument; for he that writes on Thoughts, writes on the pride and perfection of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, on that which muſt yeild us in a great meaſure the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factions or Torments of the other Life, Thoughts <hi>excuſing</hi> or <hi>accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> their Owners. He writes on that which is an unanſwerable Proof of a divine, ſpiritual, and immortal Principle of Life and Motion in us: For I defie all the Advocates of Deiſm or Atheiſm it ſelf to conceive matter, howſoever thinn'd or modi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, capable of thinking; for no man, I am ſure, if he rightly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults his own Principle of Thought, can poſſibly reconcile himſelf to this apprehenſion, that Matter, pure Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, can think, meditate, deliberate, reflect, be witty, argue, infer, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue long chains of Conſequences, and impart to man that vivacity and
<pb facs="tcp:53603:9"/> ſprightlineſs of Spirit, and that vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Genius that diſplays it ſelf in him.</p>
            <p>In a word, if any one is made <hi>wiſer,</hi> but eſpecially <hi>better</hi> by what is here offer'd, I have my end.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53603:9"/>THE Government OF THE THOUGHTS.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <p>HE that deſigns to write of Thoughts, had need tell the World, in the firſt place, what he means by the Subject of his Diſcourſe, for this is a vaſt Argument in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, as wide as the exerciſe and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all the Powers, and Faculties of the Soul, and had need therefore be determin'd to ſome particular kind or Species of its operations; for there's no ſayling to any profit or pleaſure in ſo wide an Ocean, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53603:10"/> firſt whither you are bound, and what determinate Port you ſteer for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THEN by Thoughts we do not underſtand thoſe motions that paſs in the lower Region of the Soul, the Paſſions or Affections that are excited in the Will, or in the ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Appetite, as ſome love to ſpeak; theſe may indeed be touched upon now and then, by the by, but not otherwiſe. For beſides, that it is not my deſign here to write a Book of Ethicks, as the Argument, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in that latitude, would oblige me to do, the Paſſions or Affections are not Thoughts, in propriety of ſpeech, but the effects or products of them, Thoughts are the Parents, Paſſions the off-ſpring, for by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reflecting, and the brooding of the upper powers of our Souls, our Paſſions are form'd and brought forth in us; as the muſing on an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable object, that we apprehend as preſent, raiſes in us joy; on one that is yet in expectation, hope and deſire; as, on the contrary the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53603:10"/> Thoughts of an object that is diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, creates in us fear, anger, or ſorrow, according as we conceive it preſent, or in futurity. Nor</p>
            <p n="2">II. DO I intend to ſpeak here of all the ſeveral operations that are tranſacted in the upper Region of the Soul, the Underſtanding, as of its ſimple perceptions, forming of propoſitions, diſcuſſive, and retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or recollecting power; the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Thoughts, in this acceptation of the Word, would oblige me, to direct how to form true, and diſcover falſe reaſonings, which is the Province of the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and would oblige me to run out into thoſe jejune and dry ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, that are improper for a practical deſign.</p>
            <p>I mean then by Thoughts here, neither the Paſſions, nor yet the reaſoning, deliberating, and arguing faculty of the Mind, but that power chiefly, whereby we firſt of all gaze at, contemplate, muſe upon, and converſe with thoſe images of things,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53603:11"/> which our ſenſes, for the moſt part originally repreſent to our fancies, and our fancies from them, paint forth in our minds. Any man who gives himſelf the liberty to think, and can make his Underſtanding the object of its own contemplations, is conſcious to himſelf of theſe primary interviews of his mind with the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects let into it, and muſt own them antecedent to, and conſequently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from, both his paſſions and reaſonings about them, for a Man muſt firſt think, or look upon and view the ideas in his mind, before he can be any ways affected with, or argue or deliberate about them, as a man, for inſtance, muſt firſt think upon a formidable object, before he fears it, or reaſons with himſelf how to eſcape the danger, that threatens him.</p>
            <p>NOR can it poſſibly, in the Third place, be expected that I ſhould treat of Thoughts in this limited ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of them, according to the vaſt variety of objects, that are their ſubject matter, for theſe were an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53603:11"/> argument, in the language of the Book of <hi>Job, as high as heaven, what</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>canſt thou do, deeper than Hell, what canſt thou know? The meaſure thereof is longer than the earth, and broader than the Sea.</hi> Nor God, nor the whole frame, and oeconomy of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture terminate the Horizon, or bound the ramble, and excurſions of our Thoughts, which extend themſelves even to <hi>things that are not,</hi> that have no other being but what they bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from a confus'd imagination, for our fancies, by a tumultuary compounding of ideas, inſtead of real, can create fictitious objects for their entertainment, and divert themſelves as well with a chimaera of their own manufacture, as with the moſt real and ſubſtantial Being.</p>
            <p>IT will be ſufficient therefore, and indeed all that can well be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd on this argument, to draw the great and general lines of ſeveral of thoſe excentric motions incident to our thoughts, and to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preſcribe the regulation of them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:53603:12"/>
            <p> BUT to recommend a deſign of this nature to the minds of men with better ſucceſs, it will be requiſite, in the firſt place, to premiſe ſome of thoſe many obligations that lye upon us to govern our Thoughts as well as our exterior words and actions.</p>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>AND firſt, we are obliged to this government of thoughts, becauſe we may tranſgreſs the divine Law by them, as well as by the tranſactions of the outward man. 'Twas a fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental ſlaw in the Righteouſneſs of the Scribes and Phariſees, and indeed of the generality of the whole Jewiſh Nation, that they thought an external obedience to the Law, which exempted them from all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral penalties due to the violation of it, ſufficient to denominate them righteous, without any regard had to the innocency of their hearts and affections. 'Tis no ſtrange thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that the Heathens generally, who were left to diſcover the divine
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:53603:12"/> Nature with the naked eye of their own faculties, ſhould content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſuch an external righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or obedience as this, which reached the outward man only, but 'tis a very ſurprizing conſideration that the Jews themſelves ſhould take up with it, who knew their Law to have been enacted by a God, that is a ſearcher of hearts, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the ſervice of the ſpirit, and will be lov'd and obey'd with all the powers and faculties of the mind. But yet thus it was with that ſlow and carnal people: they had very little concern upon them for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of the Precepts, that related to the regulating the motions of the inner man, for there being no penalties expreſly annexed to them, they look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on them as <hi>advice</hi> rather than <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grat.</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.</note> or at worſt, that the guilt, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by their mental ſins, was ſo done away by their ſacrifices, that God would remember them no more. They underſtood little or nothing beyond the political Covenant, the terms whereof chiefly influenc'd their obedience, and ſo took up with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53603:13"/> ſuch a political righteouſneſs, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the obedience of the civil Laws of the Jewiſh Common-weal; hence it is that <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> ſays, that the Goſpel Precepts, meaning thoſe that command the obedience of the heart and affections, ſeem'd to him incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of obſervance; and that <hi>Joſephus</hi> reprehends <hi>Polybius</hi> the Hiſtorian, for aſcribing the death of <hi>Antiochus</hi> to ſacriledge intended, tho' not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<q>For as long, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> as he did not actually execute his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he deſerv'd no puniſhment;</q> and that this was the old received notion of obedience, appears plainly enough from our Saviours correcting this miſpriſion, in the <hi>5th.</hi> of St. <hi>Mat. ye have heard,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>that it was ſaid by them of old time, thou ſhalt not kill;</hi> if a man did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually murder another, he was thought to have kept within the bounds of the eight Commandment, as indeed he did, as to the temporal penalty annex'd to the violation of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53603:13"/> it, which was then principally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded; but our Lord tells them plainly, <hi>Verſe</hi> 22. that the guilt in this particular, lies as deep as the very beginnings, the firſt efforts and ſallies of an angry mind towards a fooliſh quarrel that may end in blood, in which ſenſe St. <hi>John</hi> affirms, that <hi>whoſoever hateth his brother is a murderer,</hi> is already ſo, tho his ſword be ſtill unſheath'd, and he has ſtab'd him only <hi>in effigie;</hi> again, ſays he, to the ſame purpoſe, at the <hi>27th.</hi> ver. <hi>ye have heard that it was ſaid by them of old time, thou ſhalt not commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,</hi> if a man did but refrain from the actual embraces of a forbidden bed, how keenly ſoever he debauch'd by the ſtrength of an impure imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, yet he was, for all that in their notion of obedience, a chaſt and modeſt man ſtill, but our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tells them a rape may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the fancy, and adultery by a wanton glance. And that this Jewiſh notion of obedience, is not yet altogether antiquated under Chriſtianity, ſeems but too evident from that trite proverbial ſaying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53603:14"/> us; that <hi>thoughts are free;</hi> as if when men durſt not let looſe their hands, or their tongues, to work wickedneſs, yet they might give their deſires and imaginations their full ſwing; and muſe, and wiſh, and contrive, and pleaſe themſelves with the Invention and Images of thoſe things which they think it not ſafe to put in execution; whereas, on the contrary, the Laws of our Lord preſcribe to our affections, ſet bounds to our fancies, regulate our deſires, direct our intentions, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern our wiſhes, ſtrike at ſin in em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio, and check the firſt voluntary motions and tendencies of the mind to evil. Voluntary, I ſay, becauſe 'tis hard to imagine that thoſe <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus primò primi,</hi> as the Schools ſpeak, thoſe firſt ſtirrings of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence which come not within the verge and compaſs of the Will, ſhould fall under the laſh and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Law; a Souldier is not puniſhed for having an enemy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, but for not doing his duty to repel his aſſaults, if, inſtead of watching and repreſſing his motions,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53603:14"/> he rather entertains him, then, but not till then, let the Law go upon him. God will certainly puniſh no man for an imperfection that is not in his power to prevent, and which he did not himſelf voluntarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, will not call us to an account for being proper Subjects of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations of his Grace, but for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing it, and will not require it at any mans hands that he has the <hi>Seeds</hi> of evil ſcatter'd in his compoſition, but for ſuffering them to <hi>fructifie</hi> in the ſoil. However, it muſt ſtill be own'd that as to all the irregular motions of the inner man, that fall under the diſpoſal of our Wills, God hath concluded them all under ſin, that, by <hi>the wicked man's forſaking his thoughts,</hi> the numberleſs vain thoughts that fly up and down his mind; he might the <hi>more abundantly pardon,</hi> Iſ. 55. v. 7. accordingly the ſame Prophet tells us of thoſe that <hi>err</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſ. 29. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>in ſpirit, Solomon</hi> of thoſe that err in imagining evil, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 22. and <hi>Micah</hi> denounces woe to <hi>the deviſers</hi>
                  <note place="margin">21.</note> 
                  <hi>of iniquity.</hi> Hence the ſame wiſe King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> tells us in one place,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53603:15"/> that <hi>the thought of fooliſhneſs is ſin;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 26.</note> in another place, that <hi>they err who deviſe evil;</hi> in a third, that <hi>the thoughts of the wicked are an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord;</hi> as his Father <hi>David</hi> had before obſerv'd of ſome that <hi>their inward parts were very wickedneſs,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 2.</note> and tells us of others that <hi>in their heart work wickedneſs,</hi> hence again it is that St. <hi>Peter</hi> requires <hi>Simon Magus to repent of the thoughts of his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>heart</hi> (for what is the ſubject of our Repentance but our Sins,) that St. <hi>Paul</hi> requires us to <hi>bring into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>captivity every thought to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt,</hi> which ſuppoſes that of themſelves they are naturally rebellious; that our Saviour reprehends the Phariſees for <hi>thinking</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 9. 4. <hi>Matt.</hi> 15. 18, 19. <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>evil,</hi> and affirms of <hi>evil thoughts</hi> that <hi>they defile the man,</hi> as well as when they ſhoot forth into the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior actions of murder, adultery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The very intention and deſire whereof he elſewhere equals with overt tranſgreſſions of the kind. The reaſon of all is, that God being the Father of the Spirits of all fleſh, and the Kingdom of his Son a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53603:15"/> ſpiritual Kingdom too, 'tis congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both to the divine Nature, and ours, which is a ſtricture of his, that his Laws bear ſway in our ſpiritual part, in our hearts and ſouls, our wills and affections; for would we have an infinitely glorious Spirit ſerv'd by dull fleſh and blood only, and not rather like himſelf, in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and in truth, with thoſe prime productions, thoſe firſt born Sons of the immortal Nature in us? Has God made us men, and would we pay him but the ſpiritleſs ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the animal part of us? Has he implanted a noble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal principle of life and motion in us, and ſhall it not ſhare in our obedience to him, and conſequently in the guilt of the tranſgreſſion of his Laws? He is the natural Lord of both Soul and Body, has bought them with a Price, and therefore all the Reaſon in the World the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience we pay him ſhould be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to the extent of his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe; ſo that if we have any juſt abhorrence of Sin in the true Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Divine conſtruction of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53603:16"/> it, we muſt govern our Thoughts, as well as obſerve meaſures in our words and actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>BUT I ſhall farther evince the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations that lie upon us to order our Thoughts aright, from ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations as ſeem to enhance the guilt of mental ſins above thoſe of the outward Man. For</p>
               <p n="1">I. THO' it be an argument that ſin has acquired an arbitrary power over us, and that the Law in our members has got the aſcendent over the Law of our minds, when the ſeeds of evil thoughts ſhoot forth into criminal words and actions, and in this reſpect the off-ſpring is worſe than the Parent, that is, 'tis worſe to ſpeak and do evil than barely to think it, yet conſider the outward acts of ſin ſeparately and apart by themſelves, abſtracted from thoſe previous cogitations that give them birth, and then the ſins of the mind
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53603:16"/> are infinitely more criminal, for is it not worſe to proſtitute an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul to ſin and folly then a mouldering Caroaſe? the one is in the nature of the Artificer that models and contrives the ſin, the other but as the inſtrument as it were in its hand, and who reckons the murdering ſword as faulty as he that dar'd to ſheath it in his brother? the one is as the mother of the ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious brat, or the womb wherein luſt firſt conceives till the heart grow big and the reckoning of the ſin be out; the other only comes and mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives it into the world, and brings, forth that which <hi>brings forth death,</hi> and who ever thought theſe two equally criminal? nay, ſet aſide the guilt that derives from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the mind, and why ſhould the worſt actions of the outward man be reputed any more ſinful than thoſe of the horſe and the mule that have no underſtanding? for ſin is properly in the Soul only; the proper ſubject both of it, and of that grace which corrects it.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53603:17"/> II. OUR Thoughts are always <hi>firſt in the tranſgreſſion,</hi> and ſo in reſpect of precedency, are more inexcuſable than outward actions; they are ring-leaders in the rebellion of ſin againſt God, and perſons of that Character are generally made, as exemplary in their puniſhment as they are in their crime; theſe are the firſt begotten of their Father the Devil, the eldeſt Sons of ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal corruption, <hi>the might and the beginning of the ſtrength</hi> of ſin in us. <hi>Out of the heart proceed evil thoughts, murders,</hi> &amp;c. There the Son of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence firſt layes his ſcene of blood, the Extortioner of oppreſſion, the Adulterer of the forbidden bed, and ſo of the reſt, for a man firſt <hi>deviſes miſchief,</hi> in the Pſalmiſts language, and then <hi>puts himſelf in a way that is not good, and abhorreth not evil:</hi> nay they are not only thus the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils puny Counſel, that open the Cauſe and make a Motion in behalf of ſin, but they are perpetually ſoliciting, abetting and pleading its Cauſe at the Bar of a debauch'd fancy and a bribed underſtanding,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53603:17"/> where many times they unhappily carry it; for 'tis no wonder that a corrupt Judge ſhould give it on their ſide. Thus do our Thoughts cater and <hi>make Proviſion for the Fleſh to fullfil the luſts thereof,</hi> bring and recommend the beloved Object to the Heart till it dotes and commits actual Folly with it; thus they lay in fuel for our Sins, and not only enkindle, but blow up the fire into open flaming wickedneſs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:</p>
               <p n="3">III. SINS of Thought are more criminal than outward Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, in as much as the guilt of the one derives from the other, for all Thoughts are Errors as it were, of the firſt concoction, which affect nature in all her ſubſequent opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of life. Thoughts are as the Principal, outward acts but as Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſories. The one is in the nature of the cauſe, the other of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for <hi>out of the abundance of the heart does both the mouth ſpeak</hi> and the hands act, and <hi>out of it,</hi> ſays the wiſe man, <hi>are the iſſues of life,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:53603:18"/> and I add of death too And who can blame the ſtreams for their neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry partaking of the pollutions of their fountain? Thoughts then are the <hi>principle</hi> of ſpiritual life, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual death in us, that great lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wheel within the engine, which as when it moves regularly, it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the outward <hi>hand</hi> of our words and actions to <hi>point</hi> right, ſo when tis out of courſe, it puts all in the like diſorder with it; for our actions will be of a piece with our thoughts, and no one acts like a wiſe man, who thinks like a fool. <hi>O genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vipers,</hi> ſays our Lord to the Phariſees, <hi>how can ye, being evil, think good things?</hi> for, <hi>who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?</hi> who can bring good words or deeds out of fooliſh, wandering, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallow'd thoughts? for, <hi>how ſhall a man reap there where he has not ſow'd?</hi> can he from weeds reap grain, <hi>gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. IF we govern not our thoughts, they will govern us, or,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53603:18"/> to ſpeak more properly, will leave us without any true government of our ſelves, they are natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that need no winding up, but are inceſſant in their motion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards good or evil, and therefore if we take not care to determine them to proper objects, they will run out upon any that come in their way, will haunt and dog us to the table, to the bed, to the cloſet, to the Church, will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually intruding, interpoſing, and interrupting us in our duty, will either intercept all good motions, or diſtract and confuſe us in the performance of them, and to be ſure, will be moſt buſie and impertinent at the time of our religious ſervices, when we are to compoſe our Souls to the ſevereſt ſobriety and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſeneſs of Meditation.</p>
               <p n="5">V. THE peculiar malignity of evil Thoughts is farther viſible in this, that they render the outward act of ſin more or leſs criminal, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they have been more
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53603:19"/> or leſs active in the contrivance of it: for every previous reaſoning, premeditation, and debate, enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces its guilt and inflames its puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as that which argues a more ſtudied and deliberate contempt of the ſupreme Legiſlator, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was that the murder of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> was more charged upon <hi>David</hi> than his adultery with <hi>Bathſheba.</hi> He took a great deal of thought about the one, but in the other thoughts took him.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. SINS of Thought have this particular aggravation above outward breaches of the Law, that they are committed upon leſs temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation than theſe, and the weaker the temptation, the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is the ſtrength of ſin in us. The two great leading Paſſions of the Soul that determine us to, or deter us from, outward acts, are our hopes, or our fears, which carry many times ſo fatal and ſo ſtrong a byas with them, that they incline us to evil, even con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53603:19"/> to the checks and reluctancies of our own minds.</p>
               <p>ILL times may ſcare men into thoſe actual complyances, which left to themſelves, they abhor, and the impending danger, which, as it bore a mighty ſtroke in the commiſſion of the ſin, ſo, tho it cannot juſtifie it, yet will it make ſome abatement of its guilt, but Thoughts are, in this ſence, free, free from all external compulſion, nor priſons can confine them, nor fire nor ſword force them into a complyance; So that if they joyn in the act, they are perfect Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers in the ſervice; and as our Thoughts are thus above the reach of fear, ſo of favour too, above the love of friends, or the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of great men, or the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of rewards, for who can pay a man for that which no man knows, but the Spirit of a man which is in him; how ſhall out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hopes influence the inward tranſactions of ones own breaſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53603:20"/> external acts of ſin indeed may have ſomthing to ſay for themſelves, becauſe they may chance to carry their wages, ſuch as it is, along with them, but he who plays the knave, the adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, the murderer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in his own heart, he has nothing in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for his Soul, but ſins for pure ſinnings ſake, as it were without any proſpect of ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſider'd for his pains, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other wages than the old ſtanding one of death.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. AND Laſtly, thoſe Sins which have a more immediate rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the mind and ſpirit, as pride envy, ambition, malice, unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, uncharitableneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are tranſacted moſtly in the inner man, as they are more incorrigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo conſequently more crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, than others. For as to thoſe Vices which in a high meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the tempers and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of our Bodies, want of fuel will in time dead their flame,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53603:20"/> when the ſpirits flag, the blood chills, and the pulſe beats low, and the evil days come on wherein we have no pleaſure in them, the decays of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſet the Soul then at ſome tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſort of liberty to reflect upon her own condition; but as to the other, age generally only ſerves to confirm and eſtabliſh us in them. For how rarely do we ſee a covetous wretch let go his hold of the earth, tho' he is dropping into it? how ſeldom are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and malice exchang'd for content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and good nature? and when ſee we the proud ambitious man reduced to the ſame level of mind with his humble neighbours? Sins of this kind have too much of the Aethiopian's skin, and the Leopard's ſpots, eaſily to admit the laver of regeneration. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly we find the Angels, <hi>who kept not their firſt ſtation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in everlaſting chains under darkneſs to the Judgment of the great day,</hi> for ſins of this incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible kind. For ſuppoſe their ſin pride and ambition, malice or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53603:21"/> envy, or what you will, 'twas certainly tranſacted in the mind, without the intervention of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral efficiency, and deriv'd it's peculiar venom from the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of its nature. Mental ſins then were the firſt and are ſtill, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in themſelves, the moſt cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provocations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4. <hi>Other Reaſons why we ſhould govern our Thoughts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BESIDES what has been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto alledg'd on this behalf, the conſideration of God's all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye ought alſo to influence the conduct of our Thoughts: they lie not indeed within the walk of humane juſtice, are without the ken of humane inſpection, no eye can pry into the receſſes of the heart, but God ſees, and knows, and reads their ſubtileſt motions and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt intrigues with greater perſpicaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53603:21"/> then we do men's outward words and actions: For <hi>lo there is not a thought,</hi> not the motion of the leaſt fibre in our hearts, <hi>but he knoweth it altogether, knoweth it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off,</hi> at the diſtance of Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty it ſelf, e'er we or our thoughts had any other being than in the Divine Idea. For <hi>no thought can</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 42. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>be witholden from him. Hell and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>deſtruction are before him, how much more then the hearts of the Children of Men?</hi> And then how ſtrongly are we obliged to keep good order there, ſince they are under the eye of ſo intimate and accurate an Obſerver of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal motions, and ſubject to the inſpection of ſo true a Judge of good diſcipline, and ſo ſevere an Avenger of bad? But I ſhall urge this conſideration farther in it's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, as a means to aſſiſt us in the ordering of our thoughts aright. And therefore,</p>
               <p>II. IN order to this end, it would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſidered that God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53603:22"/> bears a ſpecial regard to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of our hearts and affections: For tho bright and ſhining Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Vertue diffuſe a luſtre round about them, promote the divine honour, and induce men to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the great Father of ſuch bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Lights which is in Heaven, yet nothing is ſo unexceptionable a demonſtration of the power of Grace and the ſincerity of our hearts, as a conſcientious care and management of thoſe Thoughts that fly up and down in them; for where ſuch an obedience is yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the divine commands as no eye can pry into but that which is ten thouſand times brighter than the Sun in its Zenith, it cannot poſſibly admit of the leaſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture, or ſuſpition of by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, but muſt be tender'd God purely for his own Sake; from a true ſpiritual principle of life, and in a ſpiritual manner; and then what ſacrifice can poſſibly be more acceptable to our Maker than the immediate iſſues and emanations
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53603:22"/> of our Souls, when there is no Stander by, no Witneſs of what paſſes betwixt God and our Souls in private, no ſecular conſideration that can poſſibly ingage us, nor temporal rewards to induce, nor temporal puniſhments to force us to the diſcharge of ſo ſpiritual and hidden a duty?</p>
               <p>III. 'TIS a main point of Wiſdom and Argument of good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to be able to order our Thoughts aright, and the acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that noble Character ſhould ſpur us on to this diſcipline of our minds: All the reaſonable World will allow him to be a penſon of a vaſt compaſs of underſtanding, who by foreſeeing and providing againſt the exigences of State, by knowing how to compound, temper, and qualifie the different intereſts, paſſions, and perſwaſions of Men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> prudently adminiſters a Government; and if ſo, no leſs will he deſerve the Character, who governs his Thoughts well for they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53603:23"/> are a Great people for number, and as mutinous and diſorderly as the moſt tumultuous rabble, ſo that they <hi>who rule well,</hi> in this ſenſe too, <hi>are worthy of double Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IV. AND Laſtly, let the conſideration of the noble and dignified Nature of our Thoughts induce us to an orderly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of them: for they are beams of that Light which is inacceſſible, the immediate fruits and eldeſt Sons of that immortal Parent in us which is nearly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied to the Divinity it ſelf, and how then can we poſſibly be ſo inſenſible of our own high Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, who were framed after the Image of the Immortal God, and are deſigned to be made more ample partakers of his Nature, as to lay out our time and our pains ſo buſily as we do in the management of a Family, acquire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Eſtate, and ſupporting and adorning a mouldring Carcaſe,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53603:23"/> and yet totally diſregard the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of our thoughts, which are. the pride and glory of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? For wherein elſe but in this thinking, reaſoning, Power do we differ from the inhabitants of our ſtable or our kennel? And as this in general diſerminates our Nature from theirs, ſo, I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid, do's one Man as much differ from, and excel another, by how much he is the better Maſter of his thoughts, and can lay them out to more generous purpoſes; if therefore we have any juſt ſenſe of the dignity of our humane Nature, and would advance and improve that part of us which is properly the Man, we muſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage thoſe thoughts by which we manage all things elſe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53603:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p>HAVING thus endeavour'd to lay before Men the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations they are under to order their thoughts aright, I ſhall in the next place point out ſeveral of thoſe Infirmities, Irregularities, and Defects, that are incident thereto, whereby it will more particularly appear, how Vain, and Frivolous, and Sinful they are. The Multiplicity of Objects and the great Variety of thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whereby the mind entertains her ſelf with them, renders it next to impoſſible to take in this argument in ſuch a Latitude as to be able to deſcend to minute par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; I ſhall therefore content my ſelf to inſtance in ſome more general defects and weakneſſes of the thinking Power in us, leaving it to every Man, who expects a more exact draught of them, to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53603:24"/> attend to the motions of his own mind and to follow the jant of his thoughts after thoſe Objects that keep them moſt company.</p>
               <p n="1">I. ALL Thoughts of our hearts are undoubtedly vain that are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about criminal objects, as the gratification of any of our luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For the ſinfulneſs of the object imparts its guilt to the act of the mind that is converſant about it, no man can think of accompliſhing a revenge, a fraud, a murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
               <l>Namque ſcelus in ſe tacitum qui cogitat ullim,</l>
               <l>Facti crimen habet</l>
               <p>is the voice of both <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Theology. St. <hi>Paul. Rom.</hi> 13. requires us not to <hi>make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion,</hi> as we render it, <hi>for the ſleſh, to fullfil the luſts thereof,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Says the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal <hi>i. e.</hi> not to contrive, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53603:25"/> before hand how to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh our wicked intentions, for our thoughts always lay the plot before it thickens into the laſt ſcene of actual execution, but this head is ſo plain that I need not longer inſiſt upon it.</p>
               <p n="2">II. THOSE Thoughts muſt needs be very vain and fooliſh whoſe ſubject matter is vain and trifling: 'tis not every ones portion, to have their minds fraught with ſolid and ſubſtantial lading, ſome carry nothing but ballaſt, dull heavy conceptions, others carry too great a ſail, are over light and aery; others trade only in toys, in news, fancies, faſhions, Apes and Peacock feathers; neither na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor education has furniſhed all men, with proper materials, for their thoughts to work upon; and therefore, ſince the common activity of their minds will not ſuffer them to be wholly idle, what wonder if they take up with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly arguments, and converſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53603:25"/> in their Thoughts, with their dogs or their horſes, with the paſſages of the Theatre, the imaginary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of ſome Hero in a Romance, or the like, thinking to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe rather than not think at all.</p>
               <p n="3">III. As ſuch Thoughts as theſe are <hi>materially</hi> vain, becauſe their Objects are nothing worth, ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Thoughts may be ſaid to be <hi>formally</hi> ſo, <hi>i. e.</hi> When tho' the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of them is good, yet the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> of the heart in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them is not as it ſhould be. Thus, the ſame numerical Prayer may be a ſweet ſmelling ſavour from one man's mouth, and an abomination from anothers, where, tho the matter of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is one and the ſame, yet the different <hi>turn of</hi> heart and mind makes it, <hi>formally</hi> conſidered, a quite different performance. So, again, a wicked man may think of the ſame God, with a good one, where tho' the matter of his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53603:26"/> Thoughts be equally good, with the others, yet his thoughts are vain, becauſe without Spiritual Life, and Vigour in them, whilſt, by reaſon of ſuch Qualifications, the others are accepted; and 'tis very poſſible for a wicked Man to have a Thouſand <hi>materially</hi> good thoughts: and yet go to Hell in the midſt of them: He may think of God and yet he never have the more ſervice of him; he may think of Repentance, and yet continue the ſame impenitent Man he was; he may think of Death and Judgment, and yet his life be never the better. 'Tis hard if in ſuch a vaſt Lottery of Thoughts, as is played at in our minds, a very wicked Man have not now and then a good chance; and yet if he is not renewed in the Spirit of his mind, and both the Principle and Courſe of his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, better'd by them, they are none of his own Thoughts, but Injections properly, with which his Soul is haunted; and ſuch think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good things will be ſo far
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53603:26"/> from abating a Man's Guilt, that they will inhaunce his Puniſhment. In fine, as every thought of ſin is not ſinful (for a Man may think of it with Abhorrence) ſo neither do's every Thought of Piety and Religion, come under the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter it pretends to. For where the heart is carnal and vain, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrates every good motion thrown into it, from without, and like a vitiated Stomach, inſtead of afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſolid nutriment to the Soul, turns all it meets with into the morbifie matter of Sin.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. 'TIS a great vanity of our thinking Power, to leave the plain beaten Road of profitable and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Knowledge, for the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, crooked Paths of Vice and uſeleſs Speculations. The Word and Works of the Almighty, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Operations of our own minds, the wonders of the greater and leſſer World, afford more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ſtuff for our Thoughts to work upon than the wideſt capacity was
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53603:27"/> ever able to go through with; and yet ſuch is the natural activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our minds, and the fruitleſs Curioſity of ſome Men's, that they chooſe to <hi>refine</hi> upon them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly beyond uſefulneſs, often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Senſe, affect <hi>Sciences falſly ſo call'd,</hi> and ſpin cobweb Notions out of their own Brains, fit only to catch flies with. Thus has the inſipid Nicety of the Schools man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and even <hi>crucified</hi> the Word of God, putting on it a crown of Thorns too, the barbarous Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſities of their own Inventions; and made the plain intelligible Doctrine of believing in God, and living well, a torture and rack to the Brains of the learned, and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the Ignorant. They have thinn'd the doctrine of Jeſus into the fineneſs and air of the metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicks of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and made their Schools as great an Aſylum for <hi>the Diſputers of this World,</hi> as their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are for the murderer, or other malefactor. And how ſhould men gather grapes of ſuch thorns, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53603:27"/> figs of ſuch thiſtles as theſe: Such brambles of diſpute may tear and rent one's mind in paſſing through them, but can never edify it.</p>
               <p n="5">V. 'TIS another vain thought to imagine we can bring about our projects without having God in our thoughts, or by contrary means to what he has appointed; thus the Jews, as God complains by <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> in the beginning of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, had <hi>forgotten him daies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Number,</hi> and were alwaies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting with themſelves, without taking him into the conſult, by what means they might ſtave off or elude the captivity threatned them; in neglect of that only means of ſincere repentance he preſcribed them; upon which account it is, that he requires <hi>Jeruſalem, to waſh her heart from wickedneſs, that ſhe might be ſaved, and</hi> asks <hi>how long her</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jerem.</hi> 4. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>vain thoughts ſhall lodge within her.</hi> They not only feigned to themſelves that <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the City royal of The Almighty Monarch of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53603:28"/> World was Impregnable, that the Temple of the Lord there was a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Sanctuary to them, againſt all their Enemies; and that it was impoſſible for <hi>Abraham's</hi> Seed to be in Bondage, to any Power upon Earth (in all which vain imaginations they were confirm'd by the falſe Prophets that abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt when the State was moſt corrupt) but that if they were at any time attack'd by the Chalde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, they would ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſtrength of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> by entring into a Confedracy with <hi>Egypt;</hi> tho God' had denounc'd ſeveral woes long before againſt that Project. And how common a thing it is for Men to leave the mighty Counſeller out of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, to truſt in an arm of fleſh, and purſue the Maze and Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth of their own devices, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing the deſigns they have upon the Anvil: We need no other, and can have have no better argument to convince us than our own Experience of the wicked pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53603:28"/> this day ſet on foot by the grand Incendiary of <hi>Europe.</hi> There is no Subject doubtleſs, whereon our Thoughts are more buſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, than in framing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving thoſe deſigns we have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun; And yet, which proves the extream Vanity of
'em, for the moſt part to little or no purpoſe. For, <hi>Man's goings are of the Lord,</hi> how much ſoever he thinks them of himſelf, and how then, as the wiſe King asks the queſtion, <hi>can a Man underſtand his own Ways?</hi> We project, deviſe, propoſe Ends, proſecute, apply Means; and yet all the while are managed, acted, and, as often as the divine Wiſdom pleaſes, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled and defeated, by an inviſible Hand behind the Curtain; for, <hi>I know, O Lord,</hi> ſaies the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, that the way of Man is not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>in himſelf, 'tis not in Man that walketh to direct his own Steps.</hi> And in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> he has particularly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſ.</hi> 30. 1, 2.</note> Wo to them who <hi>take Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel but not of Him, who ask, but</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:53603:29"/> 
                  <hi>not at his Mouth,</hi> the practice of Stateſ-men amongſt his own Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the caſe before mention'd, and for which reaſon, as he there threatens, he afterwards made the ſtrength of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (wherein they truſted) <hi>their Shame, and their</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Truſt in the ſhadow of</hi> Egypt <hi>their Confuſion.</hi> For in the excellent Language of the Apoſtle upon this
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 19, 20.</note> Argument: <hi>The Wiſdom of this World is fooliſhneſs with God: For, it is written, he taketh the wiſe in their own Craftineſs. And again, the Lord knoweth the Thoughts of the wiſe that they are vain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. THERE is another vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Thought, which our Lord himſelf takes ſuch expreſs Notice of, and that in his excellent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Mount, that it muſt not here be diſregarded by us; and that is an intemperate Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Anxiety of Thought, for the things of this preſent Life; the vanity whereof he evinces with a force of Argument, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53603:29"/> Strain of words, like himſelf, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Divine, and which will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abundantly ſuperecede, any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther illuſtration of the matter: For, Firſt, he argues <hi>a majori ad minus. Is not Life more than Meat,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Body than Raiment?</hi> i. e. Will not he, think you, who firſt kindled in you the vital flame, furniſh you with fuel to keep it in? Will not he who gave you a body; give you a covering to it? Then Secondly, he reaſons from inſtances of God's Providence to Creatures, of a nature far inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to Man, from his <hi>feeding the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 26. <hi>V.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>Fowls of the Air; and his cloathing the Lillies of the Field.</hi> Thirdly, he ſhews the vanity of this Anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Thought, from its inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficancy and ineptitude, to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of what we propoſe to our ſelves from it, for <hi>which of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>you,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>by taking thought can add one Cubit to his Stature,</hi> or, as others expound the place, can with all his anxiety, add the leaſt proportion to his Age, or extend
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53603:30"/> the period of his Life. And then as he adds, in St. <hi>Luke's</hi> relation of the paſſage, <hi>if ye are not able to do that thing which is least, why take ye Thought for the reſt?</hi> If ye are not ſufficient of your ſelves to preſerve your Lives till to Morrow, why ſo infinitely buſie to make proviſion for them? Fourthly, he tells 'em plainly, that for his followers to lay out their Thoughts ſo immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately about the affairs of this Life, is to be ſtill upon the ſame level with a gentil Spirit, <hi>for after</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>all theſe things do the Gentiles ſeek, beſides that your Heavenly Father knoweth that you have need of all theſe Things:</hi> And he is not ſo unnatural a Parent as to let his Children go deſtitute of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary accommodations of humane life. Thus has our Lord himſelf in an ample and extraordinary Manner, expos'd the vanity of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of our Thoughts to our hands, and we ſhall have occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to inſiſt farther on the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereafter.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53603:30"/> VII. THERE is a certain dulneſs or ſtupidity incident to the thinking Power, when the mind does not go, but, like a clock with the plummets off, ſtands ſtill, is heavy and dumpiſh, and has no diſtinct conceptions of any objects let into it, but nodds and and falls aſleep, as it were, and runs into another World, as Men in dreams do. And this, I conceive, is generally occaſion'd, where it is not owing to a natural Defect, either by guilt within, or troubles and dangers from without. Firſt, Guilt within, is alwaies apt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe our Reaſonings, choak and break in upon our Apprehenſions of things, and ſtrangle our Thoughts; it alwaies lies Croſs and Heavy in our mind and deads that Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Alacrity of thinking that Innocence naturally gives it. And then, Secondly, for Dangers and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters, they fix the mind upon the contemplation of the Object that Frights or Diſquiets it, render a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53603:31"/> Man's Spirit dead, as it were, within him, congeal his Powers, make them ſtiff and deſtitute of motion, ſo that a man has not for that time the command of his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to look about and provide fit means to eſcape the danger that threatens him.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. 'TIS another miſcarriage in the management of our thoughts when we propoſe no one good and fixed End of Life, for the ſupream Object of our Purſuit. Some have working imaginations never idle, alwayes ſtickling, but as good ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a whit as never the better, as the Phraſe is. For it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a Man to have this or that particular End in his View, as opportunity preſents, and his occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion require: But he muſt have a further and a fairer Mark, at which he aims and directs them all: A Man may make this or that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as occaſion ſerves in his voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but ſure every motion he makes is in ſubſerviency to gain ſome one
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53603:31"/> determinate port of Traffick, for otherwiſe, as the one ſails uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, and to very little purpoſe, ſo the other thinks and lives but from hand to mouth, as we ſay; by breaks and by parcels, without any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and coherence in Thought or Action; he purſues no one Road of Life, but takes into every by-path and his Thoughts like a wanton Spaniel in its range, run after eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry accidental Game that comes in their way.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Eſt aliquid quò tendis, &amp; in quod dirigis arcum?</l>
                  <l>An paſſim ſequeris corvos teſtâque lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toque</l>
                  <l>Securus quò pesferat, atque ex tempore vivis?</l> 
               </q>
               <p n="9">IX. ANOTHER ſinful weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Thoughts is ſeen in their being ſo much at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of our paſſions, as, if you obſerve it, they generally are, for tho Thoughts are originally ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53603:32"/> to our paſſions, as a Man muſt firſt think before he can be affected with Joy, grief, anger. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet when theſe paſſions are once up, they command the Thoughts that made them, and imploy them wholly on thoſe objects that raiſe and affect them: So that look what affections bear the ſway in a Man's heart, that way his thoughts will take their courſe; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, tho a man muſt firſt think before he can be angry, yet when that Paſſion is once upit lays out for that time all the Thoughts of an unſanctified Heart upon the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Affront or Injuſtice done one, and the means whereby we may effectually reſent and revenge it. So, again when Love and Deſire have taken poſſeſſion of us, be the Object what it will, our minds are always muſing on it, <hi>Can a Maid forget her Ornaments, or a Bride her Attire,</hi> Sayes <hi>Jeremy,</hi> the things they love and delight in? No: Our Thoughts are always preſent with their beloved Object,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53603:32"/> run after it and into it, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it to us with far more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages than it really carries along with it. And the like might be ſaid of any other of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: They diſcompoſe our minds, confuſe our Souls, and like a too powerful Enemy breaking in upon us, put the numerous Army of our Thoughts into diſorder, ſo that when the heat of the Battle is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a Man looks back upon the defeat with Sorrow and Regret; and is at a vaſt expence of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to rally up his ſcatter'd good Thoughts again, and to put them once more in a poſture of defence againſt thoſe inteſtine diſturbers of his Quiet. Now, I ſay, this is a ſignal weakneſs in our thoughts, to be thus carried away by our paſſions, at their Will and Pleaſure; for our thinking Power was given us, amongſt other Ends, to regulate and preſcribe to our paſſions, and not our paſſions to them.</p>
               <p>BUT ſince they were given
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53603:33"/> us for good Ends and Purpoſes, and we are not requir'd to eradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate but to govern them, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle's rule is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Remedy in this Caſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That we <hi>ſet our affections on things above, not upon things that are upon the earth.</hi> For our Thoughts will partake of the Qualities, and Genius of our Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; if the one are Heavenly and Divine, the other will on courſe be ſo too. <hi>David,</hi> ſpeaking of the Bleſſed Man, tells us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>That his delight is in the Law of the Lord,</hi> and then adds, that <hi>in his Law doth he meditate day and night;</hi> and in another place, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing of himſelf that <hi>he loved the divine Law,</hi> he affirms likewiſe that it was <hi>his meditation continnually.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 97.</note> For Men naturally meditate on what they love and delight in: and in <hi>Malachy</hi> the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and <hi>thinking</hi> upon his Name are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Malach.</hi> 3. 16.</note> joyned together.</p>
               <p n="10">X. THERE is another ſinful Vanity of our Thoughts, in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53603:33"/> the concerns of other Men their Objects, when they make Incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into their Neighbours Affairs, break down his Incloſures, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently ramble through all his concernments: For ſuch is the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, or Malice, or Envy, or I know not well what to call it, of ſome perſons, that they can entertain their Thoughts (as they do their company too upon occaſion) much more agreeably with other Men's matters than their own, and ev'n whilſt they keep at Home, incur the guilt of their Character whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles <hi>buſie Bodies, Tatlers, wandring</hi> (in their Thoughts) <hi>from Houſe to Houſe:</hi> The Practice of thoſe generally, who, in their own phraſe, have nothing to do, as wanting Matter, I conceive, in themſelves for their Thoughts to feed and exert upon.</p>
               <p>NOW this imployment of our Thoughts is not onely ſilly, and impertinent to any good purpoſe of Life, but 'tis criminal too, in as
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53603:34"/> much as every Man, let him have as much ſecular buſineſs as he will, yet has work enough upon his hands, the improvement of his mind, the government of his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the ſalvation of his Soul, to take up all his Thoughts, all his time and leiſure, and therefore it muſt needs be Sin in a Man, in neglect of his own proper buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to let the precious ſand of his Thoughts run out upon other Mens, where they are not call'd and have nothing to do.</p>
               <p>AND as it is a vanity of our Thoughts to gad ſo much abroad amongſt our Neighbours affairs where they have no buſineſs, ſo are they no leſs vain in this, that when they ſtay at home and turn their Eyes inward, they are apt to overlook the failings and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections of their Owners. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man has his <hi>Fort</hi> and his <hi>Foi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> his ſtrong and his weak part, his ſeeing and his blind ſide, and whilſt the eyes of our minds view
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53603:34"/> the one, even the leaſt <hi>Mote</hi> of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in us, with infinite Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency and Satisfaction, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly wink ſo hard at the other, that they let <hi>Beams</hi> themſelves e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape their Obſervation. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that <hi>doth evil hateth the Light</hi> of his own mind, <hi>neither com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the Light, leaſt his Deeds</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould be reproved:</hi> For ſelf Love is ever ready to take care that a Man fall not out with himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> ANOTHER leading im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of our Thoughts, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in their Levity or want of fixation; whereby we become <hi>as unſtable as water, and ſhall not excell: The heart of the fooliſh is like a Cart Wheel,</hi> ſaies the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach, and his Thoughts are like a rolling Axle-tree:</hi> Glib and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble in their Motions, nothing ſo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile and aery as they; they ſtream and ſhoot in an inſtant from one corner of the Earth to another, ſore as high as Heaven, and dive as deep as Hell, curvet and caper o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53603:35"/> the whole Creation, and as if that were too little for them, flie beyond the limits of the Univerſe, and the bounds of time, to Eternity and Imaginary Spaces. Like wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Spaniels they ſet out with you, and perhaps wait on you home again, but range every Field, and and purſue every game that comes in the interim in their way, or like ſome reſtleſs birds, they no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er light upon one object than they preſently take wing and fly off to another, by which means there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens many times ſo quick a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, or rather indeed ſuch a tumultuary Jumble of Ideas in our heads, that we loſe our ſelves as in a Maze, get into a Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth of our own making, and can hardly remember the goal from which our thoughts firſt ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo that if we look'd them over again, and could but trace them in their rambles and excurſions from one Object to another, we ſhould find them many times no more coherent than our Dreams,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53603:35"/> or the rovings, and extravagant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Mad-men, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the main difference betwixt the Mad-man in Bedlam, and the other muſing in his Study lies in this, that the one is ſo fooliſh as to utter his Conceptions as they throng into his head, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo wiſe as to conceal them.</p>
               <p>NOW there may be ſeveral cauſes of this Imperfection; if we will trace it up to its ſpring head, we muſt go as far back as the Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> for it, when the mind leaving the purſuit of the chief and ſupream Good, about which it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly moved as about its proper Center, and propoſing to it ſelf the acqueſt of infinite other falſe and fictitious Goods in its ſtead, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came, like a wandring Star, plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and erratic in its Motions.</p>
               <p>AGAIN we may find another cauſe of this in our own Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we are all fearfully and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully made up of two very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53603:36"/> parts, Soul and Body, and yet ſo that the Operations of the Soul do in a great meaſure depend upon the temperament of the Body; now the great Inſtruments in our ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, as well as animal Operations, are thoſe ſubtle parts of the bloud call'd Spirits, which in the very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of ſome Perſons, thoſe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of a ſanguine Complexion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a fine and light Contexture, do neceſſarily cauſe a like Levity of the mind in thinking, for we cannot poſſibly help apprehending after their Motions and Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>AND as this volatility of mind is natural to ſome Conſtitutions, ſo may ſeveral accidents produce it in others, a blow upon the Head, a diſtemper in the Brain, or intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance may put the bloud into ſuch a preternatural fermentation, and ſo agitate and confuſe the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that there will neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue a like Levity and Confuſedneſs of the mind in thinking.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:53603:36"/>
               <p> BUT that which carries the moſt general and principal ſtroke in this affair is certainly the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs of our imaginations, which is often preſenting our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with fine Pictures and Images of things, which inveigle our minds to run a gadding after them, ſet the Spirits agog, divert the main ſtream of our Thoughts from their primary channel, and let them run out, like water ſpilt upon the ground, upon foreign and improper objects. So that even the moſt thoughtful men many times are not able to direct one line of Thoughts ſtreight on, but loſe ſight of the ſubject they at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with. For imagination is a buſie reſtleſs ſort of power thats ſeldom or never idle, but moſt of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erts its activity when the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is lazy and out of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. No ſooner does the tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing object from without, honour, or pleaſure, or profit, make its way through the doors of our ſenſes to our underſtanding, but this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53603:37"/> like a Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, uſhers it in, harangues upon its Excellencies, and deſires it may have audience; if a Man hankers after honour, and his temper is ambitious, the imagination preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lifts him up to one of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Pinacles</hi> of the Court, ſhews him <hi>all the Kingdoms</hi> of greatneſs, together with Followers, Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, Attendants, Retinue, and the other <hi>glories of them,</hi> ſo that the Man's Thoughts are always mounting, making ladders, as it were, to himſelf, and contriving how to climb higher. So, again if an object of profit has poſſeſs'd the mind, the fancy preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſurvey the land, to ſet off the value and conveniency of Goods laid up for many years, and falls a telling over the money, as it were, before yours eyes, to ingage you in its purſuit, and makes your <hi>Thoughts,</hi> in the Prophets language, <hi>go after your covetouſneſs.</hi> So, again, if the Idea of a pleaſurable object has ſtoln in at your eyes, the ſame faculty
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53603:37"/> preſents you with more charms than any one elſe can ſee in it, ſummons all the ſenſes to bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the ſeveral gratifications it affords them, and recommends the object ſo long till your deluded Thoughs, play the adulterer and commit folly with it, and in all theſe caſes, like a flattering Painter draws the Picture of the object far more beautiful and exact than ever the original could pretend to and by theſe means breaks off the connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Thoughts, cuts them ſhort of the object they ſhould purſue and renders them light and deſultory.</p>
               <p>NOW this defect, as far as 'tis purely caſual, or as far as 'tis na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, owing to our complex'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Soul and Body, cannot be criminal, but then comes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly under that denomination, and is ſin to us, where the natural infirmity is countenanc'd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd, eſpecially in divine worſhip,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53603:38"/> or the defect is voluntarily acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by intemperance or the like.</p>
               <p>AND now that we are upon this Head it may not be improper here to ſubjoyn other vanities of our Thoughts that are principally owing to the ſame cauſe of a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and ludicrous imagination: for indeed this power carries a mighty ſtroke with us, influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, in a great meaſure, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the judgment, the choice of the will, the purſuit of the affections, and in conſequence of all theſe, the execution of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily powers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>AND here I ſhall firſt take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that error of Thought it occaſions in us, when we apply our ſelves to the conſideration of ſpiritual and immaterial ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For being uſed to think by the intervention of Ideas from our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53603:38"/> ſenſes, which are converſant only about material objects; the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which receives theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions from our ſenſes, is apt to draw the ſame groſs Images of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>material beings, as of Spirits, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and of God himſelf; and we being uſed to view the objects we think of as they are repreſented in the looking glaſs of fancy, are apt fooliſhly to conclude, that the originals reſemble thoſe Pictures of them, and ſo make no diſtinction in our conceptions betwixt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial and immaterial objects; hence it is that we conceive Angels to be like young Boys, and the great God like a grave old Man; that very vanity of <hi>imagination,</hi> as the Apoſtle terms it, of which the Gentil World ſtood guilty, in <hi>chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the glory of the incorruptible God</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 21, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>into an Image made like corruptible Man,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>II. WE ſhall conſider that vanity which Fancy imparts to our Thoughts in relation to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53603:39"/> ſenſual and voluptuous objects; for hereby Men frame and figure to themſelves thoſe unlawful en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments which 'tis not in their power to put in execution, courting, and addreſſing, and complemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and making fine ſpeeches in their minds to ſpeculative idols of their own framing; fond Ixions that embrace the Clouds and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours of their own luſts, <hi>filthy</hi> waking <hi>dreamers</hi> that defile, not the fleſh only, but when that's out of imployment, commit inceſt with the Daughters of their own imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; an argument of great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravity of Soul this, for Men to make procurers of their Thoughts, to proſtitute their very Spirits, and put out Conſcience, that <hi>Candle of the Lord,</hi> that all may appear like Night about them, whilſt they commit their deeds of darkneſs, their imaginary rapes, whoredomes and debaucheries. We have the voice of Scripture for it, that this <hi>ſpiritual wickedneſs</hi> is adultery, without any farther progreſs in the fact. But</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53603:39"/>
               <p> III. THERE is yet a worſe vanity of the Thoughts, if poſſible, in relation to the ſame voluptuous Objects, and that is a repetition of theſe ſinful Pleaſures of the Mind, when they are paſt and gone, and have been really tranſacted. When men are not ſatisfi'd with the harveſt they have already reap'd, but muſt have a latter Marth, as it were a ſecond crop of delight in their Thoughts and imaginations; muſt renew their filthy ſcene in their own boſomes, erect a ſtage there, and their Fancies act over again the ſame brutal Comedies again, with freſh ſatisfaction. The fault this, generally, of overgrown and diſabled ſinners, dry trees that have green leaves, tho' they are paſt bearing fruit, Men whoſe vices have left them, not through ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Grace, but natural Infirmity, who lamenting not their Sins, but their Impotence, endeavour, by the ſtrength of an impure Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on yet living in them, to conjure up the Ghoſt of their old departed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53603:40"/> Luſts, to make the dry bones live, and give their dead Sins a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from one grave, whilſt they themſelves are ready to drop into another.</p>
               <p>SO, again, this mental repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of ſinful acts is ſeen in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Caſes, as when a man has overreach'd and defrauded his Brother in any kind, he is apt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly to applaud himſelf for the villany, to walk over thoſe ſteps, again in his mind, by which he circumvented him, and repeat the diſhoneſty with as much ſatisfaction as he committed it; ſo Men that are of bitter and implacable Spirits, will act over their revenge again in their Thoughts, make the wounds already given their Adverſary, bleed afreſh, in their own minds, and ſtab him once more in Eſſigie, and ſo of other Vices.</p>
               <p>NOW a Man muſt be arriv'd at a very high meaſure of Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency and Impiety, who thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulges.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53603:40"/> One would think it were enough for Men to commit the outward acts of Sin with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but to repeat them with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light again, is to approve of them upon mature advice, and boldly to declare againſt all Relentings and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentances, which ever look with horror, not with ſatisfaction, upon our by paſt evil Actions. The great Apoſtle makes it an argument of a very wicked diſpoſition, not onely to commit Sin, but to take pleaſure likewiſe in thoſe who do ſo, and if there be any difference in the caſe, 'tis certainly the worſe to be pleas'd with ones ſelf for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. For every ſuch after game of internal complacency is a freſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Sin, ſtains the Soul with a new guilt, and that ſo much the deeper, by how much 'tis the more criminal to ingage, not only the powers of the body to commit Sin, but the faculties of the Soul likewiſe to view and contemplate and repeat it.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53603:41"/>
               <p> IV. ANOTHER Vanity of Thoughts, chargeable upon a wild and ungovern'd Imagination, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveable in Men's framing fine Schemes, and Images, and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of things, and then pleaſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with them, as if they were Realities, and they actually enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them. For the Fancy has a ſort of power of Creation, and can hold up the Images of Idols of its own making, fictitious Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Riches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till the fooliſh Heart falls down and worſhips them. Thus you ſhall have Men placeing themſelves in ſome high Poſture, or eminent Station, or plentiful Fortune, and then amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves with ten Thouſand idle Projects, how they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have themſelves in ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; what figure they ſhould make, what intereſt they would drive on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Cutting out as much work for themſelves, as if they were in the actual poſſeſſion of the Fools Paradice, they have invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Theſe and the like imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:53603:41"/> are the frequent entertainment of melancholy and hypocondraick Perſons, and perhaps the beſt of Men are apt now and then to fall into theſe ſort of awaking Dreams; our minds are apt to ſpread wider than our Conditions, and we will now and then, when our underſtandings are not better imployed, be figuring as buſily to our ſelves, what we would do, if inveſted with ſuch an honour, poſſeſſed of ſuch an Eſtate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if we were actually Maſters of them. Thus our Fancies project ſhadows, and we take them for ſubſtance; we firſt build Caſtles in the Air, and then our Thoughts proudly ſtrut through every room of the imaginary Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; we frame an <hi>Idol,</hi> and then fall down and worſhip it, whilſt our <hi>Idol,</hi> in the Apoſtles definition of it, <hi>is nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>NOW this is not only a vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and a weakneſs in our Thoughts, but a Sin too. Firſt becauſe God hath provided better Objects for the entertainment of our Thoughts,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53603:42"/> than ſuch Chimeras. And,</p>
               <p>2. BECAUSE that when our minds thus ſtrowl and ſtray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Circumſtances the Divine Providence has placed us in, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a ſort of diſſatisfaction in us, with our preſent Condition, which is ever criminal.</p>
               <p>V. AS 'tis a great vanity of the mind thus to imploy its Thoughts, in imaginary Suppoſitions, or in drawing Pictures, as it were, of things, and then taking them for Realities, and Originals; ſo is it likewiſe a Weakneſs and Fondneſs in the thinking Power, owing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to a buſie Imagination, to dwell upon, and be ever contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating a Man's own real Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whether of Body, Mind, or Fortune. We are certainly our own greateſt Flatterers, and ſhould never be impos'd upon by others in this kind, did we not firſt delude and impoſe upon our ſelves. When God has bleſt Men with great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53603:42"/> of Mind, large Fortunes, or the like, they are always view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in the flattering Looking-Glaſs of their own Fancies, (like thoſe who ſpend half their time in dreſſing) or many times it proves a magnifying Glaſs, that repreſents their Enjoyments or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, in far larger Dimentions than what they have in Reality. Thus the Men of parts will be ever and anon amuſing and pleaſing themſelves with their own Notions and Productions whereby, as they are apt to over rate their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions and abilities, ſo are they inclin'd to undervalue and depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate thoſe of other Men. For whilſt our Thoughts thus dwell upon our own Perfections, they are apt at the ſame time to ſit in Judgment too upon the ſuppos'd imperfections of other Men, and thereupon fall immediately upon making Compariſons, and to be ſure bring in the verdict on their own ſides. Thus, again, in the caſe of large Revenues, Men, like
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53603:43"/> the rich Fool in the Goſpel, are ever and anon taking an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Survey of their Eſtates, an Inventory, as it were, of their Goods, telling them over, as Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do their Counters, or cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Men their old Gold, when they ſing the ſoft Requiem to their Souls of Goods laid up for many Years, take thine Eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry. Thus, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, in caſe of Reputation, for Sanctity of Life, the ſtiff ſuperci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Phariſee pleas'd himſelf migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, you may conceive, with the thoughts of his own imaginary Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and the vogue he had amongſt the People upon that account, when his Gravity was pleas'd to thank God that he was not as other Men. Now, I don't think, that 'tis abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſinful in it ſelf, to view one's own enjoyments of Fortune, abilities of Mind, and other good Qualifications, and to give one's ſelf the Advantage, if it fairly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear on one's ſide, upon a juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon (tho' great Care in the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53603:43"/> mean while ought to be had, that the miſtaken Charity of ſelf-love delude us not, in covering a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of our own Imperfections). for a ſober and temperate Perſon, For inſtance, when he compares himſelf with the Drunkard, or the chaſte Man with the Adulter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or the knowing educated Man with the Ruſtic, cannot but think themſelves placed as far above the cheap and ſorbid Level of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the cleanneſs and ſair Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the top of the Hill is above the Mire and Dirt at the Bottom. It not being indeed in the power of Men's faculties ſo to ſtifle the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their Conceptions, as to baulk all ſenſe of Advantage which they find upon the Compariſon. But here then lies the Vanity and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this Procedure of our Thoughts, that our hearts are not thereby rais'd to a Thankfulneſs to Almighty God, as the free Donor of ſuch Gifts, Abilities, and Graces, but we are apt to terminate our Thoughts within our ſelves, where
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53603:44"/> they work, and ferment, and leven all our good Qualifications, by huffing us up with Pride.</p>
               <p>VI, ANOTHER Vanity of our Thoughts, owing to the ſame cauſe of an ungoverned Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is ſeen in their forwardneſs and impatience of enjoying thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects we conceive agreeable to us; like a kind Friend, or eager Lover, that cannot ſtay at Home till the Perſon he longs for arrives, but takes horſe to meet him, and bid him welcome on the Road; for how often do our Thoughts anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate the Revenues, as I may ſay, of our actual Enjoyments, and, <hi>Chamelion</hi> like, live upon the <hi>airy</hi> hopes of Fruition: Whence the reaſon of that common Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Expectation generally has the better of it, and Men meet not with that Satisfaction in the things they expected. For beſides the Emptineſs and Nullity that there naturally is in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this World (they never
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53603:44"/> being deſign'd to fill up the large Capacities of the heart of Man) our Fancies are always repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us things more eligible than they are in themſelves, and our Thoughts have gone ſo often out before hand to meet, and converſe with their beloved Object, that they have enjoyed, and deflowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it already, and ſo have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal'd the ſatisfaction of Poſſeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p>WE will now, in the next place, inſtance in thoſe deſects which are obſerveable of our Thoughts in relation to holy Things, and the exerciſes of Devotion.</p>
               <p>AND the firſt weakneſs of our thinking Power that I would take notice of on this head, is the <hi>enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſm</hi> to which it is ſubject, when we cannot <hi>govern</hi> and <hi>command</hi> our Thoughts, cannot keep them <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> and within the bounds of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53603:45"/> but they grow wild, and fly out into Imaginations of Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Revelations, immediate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences with the Deity, extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whilſt, general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perhaps always in the latter Ages of the Church, ſuch preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions derive not from that ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and divine Principle, to which they are aſcribed, but, to ſay no worſe of them here, from cauſes purely Natural, as Conſtitution, Meditation, Diſcipline, Education, Diſtemper, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, as for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, who has not heard of the undoubted Effects of natural Melancholy in this kind. What ſtrange imaginary Scenes Men of this dark Complexion have ſo ſtrongly figured to themſelves, as firmly to believe their Reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tho' as Rediculous and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent as any in their Dreams. And as for Contemplation, which improves the former temper, what ſtudious Perſon has not obſerv'd, how wild and ungovernable his Thoughts grow upon Profound me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53603:45"/> eſpecially if dwelling upon a noble ſubject, and exalted by a ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Retirement. And then 'tis obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to imagine; how a Man, during theſe confus'd Tranſports of his Soul, may be apt to aſcribe the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his own bewildred Reaſon, as others do thoſe of their natural Conſcience, to ſome extraordinary Principle without and above them. This doubtleſs, together with a frightful gloomy Diſcipline (not to mention the advantage the Devil takes of ſuch Occaſions) is the only rational hypotheſis where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ſolve thoſe Viſions, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Conferences with the Divinity, pretended to by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſtic Meſſalians of old, the rapturous and extatick Frenſies of the famous Founder of the Jeſuits and ſome of his Diſciples, and, in ſhort, all the legendary traſh, treaſured up for the advancement of the Romiſh Superſtition. For there's no doubt to be made but that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Zeal and Bigotry in Devotion, a contemplative Life,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53603:46"/> the privacy of a Cloiſter or a Cell, together with a meloncholly Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which it either finds, or makes, has made their <hi>Prophets Fools</hi> (as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſpeaks) and their <hi>ſpiritual</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Men mad:</hi> For too much think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing has made more Mad-men than too little. If from theſe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to preternatural cauſes of theſe counterfeit Operations of God's Spirit, Diſtempers, Experience will inform us what Raptures and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are incident to hyſterical and hypocondraick Perſons. No leſs an Enthuſiaſt than <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelf is ſaid to have owed all his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Divinity to that ſacred Diſeaſe, as the Ancients call'd it, an Epilepſy. <hi>Caſaubon Of Enthuſiaſm,</hi> tells us of thoſe who through a hurt in their Brain have fancied themſelves actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in Paradiſe; and of others, that amidſt the Tranſports of their Viſions and Revelations, have died of that which produced them, a Feaver. And as to a certain ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gift, pretended to ſtill by ſome People, I believe, I could
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53603:46"/> ſhew, that a Treaſure of ſcripture Phraſes, a voluble Tongue, and a warm Temper, gradually heated and inflamed by the impetus of of delivery, together with a good aſſurance before Men, and an odd ſort of familiarity with God, has actually done the feat with the greateſt Maſters of the Talent.</p>
               <p>II. WE may obſerve a natural <hi>Averſion</hi> in our Thoughts to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meditation. When any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject preſents it ſelf that carries Pleaſure, or Profit, or the gratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of any of our ſenſual Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites along with it, O how gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily do our thoughts careſs, embrace, and bid it ten thouſand welcomes! But when God, or Religion, or Death, or Judgment, or any ſuch grave and ſerious Subject proſſers it ſelf to our Thoughts, how apt are they to ſlink away, hang back, and be ſhy, and after, it may be, a very ſhort Enterview, and a cold En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, diſmiſs thoſe Objects, make them ſtand by and give way
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53603:47"/> to ſuch as are more entertaining and diverting? The one's a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Gueſt and old Acquaintance, the other meets with the formal Reception of a Stranger, or as of a Viſitant that is not agreeable. When we wind up our minds to the higheſt Pin of Meditation on theſe Subjects, our Thoughts, after a very little ſtay there, preſently fall down again, we are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient and uneaſie under the Stretch, and care not perhaps how ſoon Buſineſs, or Company, or the like, ſtep in and ſet us at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſo averſe naturally are our Thoughts, unleſs God has ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied our Hearts, to converſe with holy Objects.</p>
               <p>III. OUR Thoughts, in regard of holy Duties, are apt to <hi>miſtime</hi> and <hi>miſplace</hi> themſelves, when, tho' they may be materially lawful and good in themſelves, yet, they intrude impertinently, at a time not proper for them, when they are not call'd upon, and have no
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53603:47"/> buſineſs in the mind, like an over officious friend, who, tho' he means well, yet mars a matter through the unſeaſonableneſs of his interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. To every thing, ſays <hi>Solomon</hi> there is time and ſeaſon, and 'tis the <hi>right ordering</hi> of things, as to time, as well as place, that renders them proper, and decent, and agreeable. A Souldier may mean very well, and do ſome acceptable Service by leaving his Rank, or quitting the Poſt aſſign'd him, and yet, for all his Succeſs, he becomes a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor; and may be call'd to an account for ſo doing: And juſt ſo it is with our Thoughts, I mean particularly in our religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances; they may be truly good in themſelves, yet if they are forreign to the matter in hand, ſtep in unſeaſonably, and break their Ranks, they are Criminals. So that when we are at our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, 'tis not enough to bar out all ſinful and worldly Conceits from crowding in upon us, but we muſt ſtave off all other thoughts
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53603:48"/> that relate not to the matter in hand; for tho' a Thought, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or purpoſe of doing ſome good Work be in it ſelf Divine, yet tis a queſtion whether or no the Spirit that ſuggeſts it at that time be Divine, becauſe it tends then only to diſtract us, and mar the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance we are about, as colour miſplaced in the face doth the beauty: ſo then, Gods worſhip, muſt be performed, not only externally, but internally too, in decency and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and we muſt not offer that great Majeſty who made all things, in weight and meaſure, a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary jumble of Thoughts in our homage to him. But as, in the words of the Apoſtle; <hi>He that is ingaged in the Ministry must wait on his Miniſtring, and he that teacheth on Teaching, and he that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth on Exhortation,</hi> &amp;c. So he that is at his Prayers, muſt attend to his Prayers, to the particular Petition before him; he that is giving Thanks to his Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he that is at Confeſſion to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53603:48"/> his Confeſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> directing all his Thoughts ſtreight upwards to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven; and he that is at Sermon, ought, for that time, to apply his whole Thoughts to what is offer'd, and if any other thoughts, howſoever lawful and good, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to interpoſe, muſt bid them come another time, for that he is now otherwiſe ingag'd, and not at leiſure.</p>
               <p>IV, 'TIS another ſinful Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in our thinking Power, that tho we are willing to entertain pious Objects in our Hearts, yet we care not to <hi>dwell</hi> long upon them, ſo that they leave not thoſe prints and impreſſions behind them that ſtick and abide by us, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not the heart with that due Fragrancy and Savour they ought to leave behind them, when they are paſt and gone; for tho we may not be ſo bad as thoſe, of whom it may be affirmed, with the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> that God is not in all their Thoughts, yet of well
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53603:49"/> diſpoſed minds it may be ſaid that he is not much at a time there: 'Tis long ere we can get ſight of him through the optick glaſs of Contemplation, and when we do, our hands ſhake, or ſomthing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſes, ſo that ever and anon we loſe ſight of him again, and this Levity of mind, as it is ſeen in our Contemplations upon any Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſo more eſpecially in the performance of holy Duties: We ſet forth in Prayer, it may be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, with a due Compoſure of mind and an humble Senſe of our obligations to God, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on Him; but perhaps e're we are got half way on with our work, our Thoughts, which ſet out with our Lips, have given them the ſlip, and left them to go on by themſelves, whilſt they in the interim have rambl'd perhaps from one corner of the Earth to another, and made the <hi>grand Tour</hi> of the World: When we ſhould earneſtly ſeek God by Prayer, and our Souls and Spirits ſhould aſcend
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53603:49"/> ſtraight upwards in direct Bays of fervent devotion, behold them toſſed like a dried leaf before the wind, or as an empty cask upon the waves; for, <hi>inſtead of good, evil is preſent with us, and we cannot do the things that we would;</hi> but the World and the Devil knock at the Door of our hearts, ſtep in, and deſire to ſpeak with our Thoughts, divert them from their buſineſs, and make a Man's heart go after his covetouſneſs, as the Prophet ſpeaks, after his pleaſures, his ſins or his ſecular imployments: any thing that was forgot before will be ſure then to preſent it ſelf to the mind and ſue for Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Nay many times foreign Thoughts come about us, like Bees, as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of his enemies, in whole ſwarms together, and with their humming noiſe diſtract our attention; or, like <hi>Abrahams</hi> Fowls, in flocks, to peck at and deform our Sacrifice. And thus, again, it is in that other Branch of Religious duty, hearing of the word, for no
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53603:50"/> doubt but any Man, upon a juſt recollection of his Thoughts, will find they were out of Church ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times whilſt his Perſon was there; at home, in the Shop, or the Coſſer, or indeed any where, but where they ſhould have been; in fine either out of Doors, or at play perhaps within, as much as the Children generally are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. But then take any other ſort of objects, pleaſurable, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, or honourable, and your Thoughts ſhall dwell, and hover, and brood over them, all the day, ſaid I, nay, in the Night too, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb your repoſe, and awake you; for <hi>the abundance of the rich,</hi> to uſe the wiſe Man's inſtance, <hi>will not ſuffer him to ſleep.</hi> And ſo it is of any other worldly project, gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men's Luſts, compaſſing a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, or the like: of the latter of which the ſame wiſe Man ſpeaks; <hi>they ſleep not except they have done miſchief, and their ſleep is taken away unleſs they cauſe ſome to fall.</hi> So intent are Men's Thoughts, ſo cloſely do
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53603:50"/> they faſten upon theſe earthly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual, and many times Deviliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, whilſt they are preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weary, and frisk off from any thing that is ſacred, and ſober, and ſerious.</p>
               <p>NOW this wandring in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and other holy duties is reſolva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble into ſeveral cauſes. As</p>
               <p n="1">I. INTO our complex'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Soul and Body. Whilſt our Souls are lodg'd in theſe pitiful tenements of Clay, they cannot help being affected with the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of their Habitation. They are confined to the uſe of Bodily Spirits in their moſt abſtracted operations, and every conſiderable diſorder in the blood and Spirits does therefore of neceſſity produce a proportionable diſorder in the Soul in thinking, and being ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with ſuch variety of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and buſineſs, whilſt we live in this material World, which through the intervention of our ſenſes, leave
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53603:51"/> their Ideas in the Head behind them, the eye of the mind can no more help looking upon them, when they are jogg'd and thrown in its way, than the eyes of our bodies can help ſeeing when they are open, or our ears hearing the ſounds that ſtrike them. All this is natural and neceſſary, as the unavoidable reſult of the dependance of the Soul in its moſt ſpiritual operations upon the frame and contexture of our Bodies during their conjunction: and we may as well think of cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be what we are, and of caſting the Man in a new mould as of a total prevention of this infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Conſtitution. And this being ſo, we muſt expect to meet with it in our Prayers, as well as in other buſineſs of our Lives; tis in Heaven alone, where the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of both Soul and Body ſhall be inlarged and refined, and we ſhall have but one Object of our Thoughts, God, who ſhall be all in all, that our Souls ſhall cleave in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably to him without the leaſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53603:51"/> avocation. All which may ſerve to qualify, by the by, the ſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and vexations incident to ſome tender minds, who are apt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to entertain too hard thoughts of themſelves, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo manage their Thoughts that they ſhall regularly attend upon Gods Service, without breaks and chaſms in them, without falling off now and then, and ſtraying from their preſent buſineſs: For 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, in the very nature of things, our Compoſition, totally to prevent the firſt beginnings, or ſallies of the Mind towards wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, for the Spirits, by whoſe intervention we perform theſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Operations, will not bear ſo rigid a fixation; all we can do in the caſe, and that we muſt do, is to keep a ſtrict eye upon our Thoughts, to drive away the Fowls that light upon our Sacrifice, to endeavour continually to check and controul and ſtop them in their ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reer to other objects, and when at any time they have given us the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53603:52"/> ſlip, to call them upon the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery home again to their buſineſs, and regret our weakneſs; and if we thus both bewail, and labour to reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy thoſe exurſions of our Thoughts which we cannot totally hinder, they are not our ſin, but infirmity, which will never affect our main ſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">II. DISTRACTING Thoughts in Prayer are very much owing to that natural averſion we obſerv'd in us to things ſpiritual and Divine, for ſuch imployment of our Thoughts being therefore a ſort of <hi>preternatural</hi> force upon them, the <hi>ſpring</hi> that bends them Heaven-ward will be apt to relax, and give way to the contrary tendency of our minds downwards, ſo that leaving thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome objects they preſently fall back again into the company of the old familiars of their thoughts.</p>
               <p n="3">III. OUR diſtractions proceed, in a great meaſure, from an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active and ungovern'd imagination: 'tis the quick-ſilver part in our
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53603:52"/> mettal, that runs glibly up and down, and ſhoots, as it were, in our minds, like Meteors in the Air, traverſing our devotions with ten thouſand frivolous and fooliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, preſenting us with thoſe fine Schemes and Images of things, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, honour, or the like, till the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted wandring Man, inſtead of his Maker, worſhips all the while perhaps the Idol of his own and the Devils making. But we have diſcours'd the extravagancies of this Faculty before.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. DISTRACTIONS in Prayer proceed frequently from an intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate love of the World and the cares that attend its enjoyments; which ſo often ingroſs our hearts, that we no ſooner ſet about holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties than they juſtle the one thing needful out of our minds, and make <hi>Mary's</hi> good part ſtand by, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 42</note> give way to <hi>Martha's</hi> concern for the World and the family. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly one of the moſt ridiculous, and yet moſt general frailties inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53603:53"/> to our corrupt nature, to uſe this World as if neither we, nor the faſhion of it were to paſs away; which is juſt as if a Traveller, with buſineſs of infinite importance on his Hand, ſhould loyter and take up with his Inn on the Road, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever farther purſuing the end of his journey. And poſſibly moſt of the ſins that are committed in the World are fairly reſolvable into a too paſſionate fondneſs for it. <hi>Ye cannot ſerve God and Mammon,</hi> is a ſaying that carries a greater force of truth in it, than poſſibly moſt Men are aware of. For their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of action are oppoſite, their intereſts are oppoſite, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a quite different frame of mind in their reſpective Votaries: and we know who has told us no leſs truly than roundly, <hi>that if any Man love the World the love of God is not in him;</hi> for it ties down our apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to things mean, and trivial, and baſe; and ſtifles and chokes our deſires of ſuch as are ſpiritual and Divine; it extinguiſhes all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53603:53"/> fervour of Spirit, eſtranges from God, and puts out that ſacred flame of love for him, which is the very life and Soul of our devotions to him; it crowds into the Church and Cloſet with us, and like the Sons of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> is too hard for <hi>David;</hi> ſo that many times, with <hi>Demas,</hi> we <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Lord</hi> in our Thoughts, even whilſt we pretend to do him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, <hi>having lov'd this preſent World,</hi> whoſe <hi>thorns (i. e.</hi> its cares and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) <hi>choak the ſeeds,</hi> in our Saviours
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 7. 14.</note> eſtimate, of all the good that is ſown amongſt them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that when God required the male Children of the Jews thrice a year to attend upon his ſervice at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he promiſed that <hi>no Man ſhould deſire their Land when they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> 34. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould go up to appear before the Lord their God, thrice in the year;</hi> for the fears and jealouſies that might other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have ſeiz'd them, would have divided their hearts betwixt God and their families at home, and ſo have blaſted the fruits of ſo laborious and univerſal a journey: and upon
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53603:54"/> the ſame account it is, that the Apoſtle adviſes ſingle perſons, that were able to receive it, to continue rather in that ſtate, in times of difficulty and diſtreſs, that they might <hi>attend upon the Lord without thoſe diſtractions</hi> of mind, that are almoſt unavoidably inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to perſons deeply intangled in ſecular concernments.</p>
               <p n="5">V. ANY reigning and prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Luſt will both obſtruct and diſtract our Devotions; for where our treaſure is there will our hearts be alſo, and eſpecially, at the time of our religious Services, will be apt to run out of the Cloſet and the Church to meet and chat with their beſt Beloved: We may indeed at ſuch junctures be proof againſt the Courtſhip of other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior temptations, and therefore the Devil takes eſpecial Care then to ſet the Sin of our boſom on work, to imploy the favourite Luſt for our Diverſion. And this is ſo uſual a ſtratagem to decoy our
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53603:54"/> hearts from our Services, that we may hereby certainly diſcover our
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 5.</note> darling topping Luſt, the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of our depraved Hearts, that which all the others pay obedience to, and do it homage, for that to be ſure is it which pretends the greateſt intereſt in us, and thereupon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs us moſt in holy Duties.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. OUR diſtractions in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er frequently proceed from thoſe Objects that ſtrike our ſenſes during the Service. For 'tis not in the compaſs of our powers to give any diſtinct and tolerable attendance to ſeveral and perhaps contrary Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at the ſame time, ſo that the Ideas of thoſe we let in at ſuch junctures, at the doors of our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, turn the mind out of its way, and divert it from the proſecution of its proper buſineſs. An open and erect ear to every ſound will make diſcord in the brain, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant eyes will cauſe a wandring heart: if <hi>Dinah</hi> like they gad abroad to ſee the Daughters of the Land,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53603:55"/> tis odds but they meet with objects in their jant that will commit a rape upon them. And therefore, we ſhould, either, with <hi>Job, make a covenant</hi> with our ſenſes when we engage in holy duties, let our <hi>eyes look right on,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, and our <hi>eye lids look ſtraight before us,</hi> or, ſhut up their Doors as much as poſſible, to exclude the foreign di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of our attention, for nothing poſſibly promotes fixation of Thought more than the cloſing of our eyes; experience tells us the darkneſs is an undoubted help to intenſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, and the Arabian Proverb imports, that when the five Windows thoſe of the ſenſe are ſhut up, the Houſe of the mind is then fulleſt of light: I might aſſign here ſeveral other negative cauſes, as I may ſtile them, of this defect, as the want of a true love of God, want of a devout habit of mind, want of preparation of the heart, before we enter upon religious duties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But theſe will fall better under the laſt general Head of diſcourſe, the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53603:55"/> regiment or government of our Thoughts upon theſe and other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions; and therefore,</p>
               <p n="7">VII. AND laſtly, There is no doubt to be made but that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions and wandrings of our Thoughts in Prayer, are, in a great meaſure, owing to the machinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and experiments of the Devil upon us; for tho' in theſe ordinary caſes we at preſent ſpeak of, 'tis a difficult, and perhaps unneceſſary task to diſcover, whether the Devil or our own Thoughts are firſt in the tranſgreſſion (for they are both ready enough to joyn in the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy againſt us) and doubtleſs Men are apt many times to charge the inbred corruptions of their own depraved nature to the account of that infernal Spirit, and ſo paint him blacker, if poſſible, than he is; And it were beſides an overnice and fruitleſs enquiry, to ſearch into thoſe artifices and methods whereby he may rationably be ſuppoſed to withdraw our attention from our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53603:56"/> Prayers; for we cannot well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine how far he may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the uſe of any of thoſe means of diſtraction we have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto mentioned, as the love of the World, the wandring of the ſenſes, the painted ſcenes of the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, and the importunities of any reigning and prevailing luſt. Nor can we with any certainty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine what feats he is able to perform upon ſuch occaſions, by outward diſturbances and inward injections; for we can gueſs but darkly at the operations of Spirits, how far or by what way they can inſinuate and communicate their motions to our minds; yet who ſo conſiders how inſtrumental he is in other ſins, as in <hi>David</hi>'s numbring the people: <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>'s
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 27. <hi>Acts.</hi> 5. 3.</note> betraying his Maſter: <hi>Ananias</hi>'s lying to the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more particularly, how much we are many times peſter'd with foreign and improper Thoughts during our approaches to the Throne of grace, whilſt we find a great eaſe and freedom in our minds when they
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53603:56"/> are ingaged in worldly Buſineſs, or in any other philoſophical or indifferent Contemplation: And who ſo reflects farther how much it is his intereſt to ſpoil and break off our Commerce with Heaven, and blaſt the Fruit of all our Prayers, ſince this viſibly advances the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of his Kingdom, muſt grant, in the general, that he is doubtleſs particularly concern'd in the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of our Thoughts during di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service. Accordingly we find that where St. <hi>James</hi> requires us to <hi>draw nigh to God,</hi> he bids us at <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 7, 8.</note> the ſame time, <hi>reſiſt the Devil,</hi> which is a plain evidence, that when we come to <hi>ſtand before the</hi> Lord, <hi>Satan ſtands at</hi> our <hi>right hand,</hi> in the Prophet <hi>Zachary's</hi> Language,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zac.</hi> 3. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ready to reſiſt us;</hi> And our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf in the parable of the Sower and the Seed, tells us plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that <hi>the Devil,</hi> or, in St. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.</note> Language, <hi>the wicked One, taketh away the Word out of ſome Mens Hearts leſt they ſhould believe and be Saved.</hi> They are the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53603:57"/> by the Way ſide, our Lord there ſpeaks of, ſuch as in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom's</hi> expoſition advert not, nor attend to what is deliver'd, your careleſs ſupine Auditors, who while the Preacher toils, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks by him, and the Holy Ghoſt is ready to co-operate, are amuſing themſelves with ten thouſand incoherent and foreign imaginations: and what the Devil is ſo ready to do at Sermons, he will think it much more his intereſt to do at Prayers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, methinks, it ſhould be a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful inducement to engage men to a ſerious attention on both thoſe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, to conſider that whilſt they are led aſide with thoſe vain imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, that interrupt their attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what they themſelves ſay to God, or others ſpeak to them in his Name, the Devil all the while, if we'l believe our Lord himſelf, is buſie with them, lays cloſe ſiege to their Hearts, and makes them more effectually ſerve him, than the Lord that bought them. Not that I look upon every ſuch aſſault and even
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53603:57"/> Succeſs of the Tempter upon us, as an argument of an irreligious temper and reprobate Mind: For the Devil, who is all Spirit, can hold out the fiege againſt us, longer than we, who dwell in houſes of Clay, can ſuſtain his Incurſions, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Infirmity of our Compoſition, where tho the Spirit may be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling yet the fleſh is weak, will neceſſarily make our minds nod, take them off their guard now and then, and conſequently give the Tempter an anavoidable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over us, yet if theſe wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings of our Spirits are grievous to our Minds upon recollection, if we hence learn what unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servants we are, even in our beſt Performances, and humble our ſelves hereupon in the ſight of God, begging him to <hi>whip</hi> thoſe <hi>Thieves,</hi> that ſteal away our Thoughts, <hi>out of the Temples</hi> of our Souls, we ſhall not ſtand chargeable with the Robberies they commit upon us, but as the motions of the good Spirit, when rejected, do ſo much
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53603:58"/> the more inhaunce Men's guilt, ſo will the injections of the evil One, when guarded againſt, as far as may be, and reſiſted, be ſanctified, through the divine Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, to our greater advantage. In fine, this wandring of the mind in holy Duties, tho in its beſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction 'tis a great Unhappineſs, yet will be only ſo far imputed for Sin to us, as it is voluntary in its Cauſe, and in our own power to remedy, and is, in its Progreſs, whence ſoever it derives, indulged and complyed with.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p>WE proceed now to another more terrible ſort of Thoughts, wherewith the Minds of Men are many times unhappily infeſted. For it is not unuſual, for ſome tempers eſpecially, to be aſſaulted with abundance of odd, extravagant, and horrid Thoughts breaking in upon them, in ſpite
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53603:58"/> of all Guard and Oppoſition. Thus you ſhall have ſome, thoſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of muſing heads and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly Diſpoſitions, preſs'd upon now and then with Atheiſtical and Blaſphemous C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gitations, tempted either, with <hi>David,</hi> to deny God, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 73. 2.</note> from a conſideration of the unequal Diſpenſation of his Providence in the World, or ſome other ſuch illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical Topick; or elſe, through the preſſure of their Afflictions, or the like, to think hardly of him, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him in his Attributes, to <hi>charge</hi> him <hi>fooliſhly,</hi> and <hi>to curſe him and die.</hi> Others you ſhall have poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd with diſmal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r having ſinned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the holy Ghoſt, of their being Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, caſt off of God, without the verge of his Mercy, and ſeal'd up for deſtruction. Others, Laſtly, there are hurried on in their minds to the commiſſion of ſome great and crying Sins, even againſt the bent of their own Propenſions; and that, ſometimes as far as ſelf Murder it ſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:53603:59"/>
               <p> NOW theſe Thoughts being all of 'em a kin, and of the ſelf ſame Family, I ſhall not go about to treat of them ſeverally and apart, but together and in the following Method.</p>
               <p n="1">I. I ſhall endeavour to ſhew that there is ſome difficulty in ſtateing their proper Riſe and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine. But that,</p>
               <p n="2">II. 'TIS of great uſe to know it, and therefore</p>
               <p n="3">III. IN order thereunto, I ſhall aſſign ſome Marks and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſties, whereby it may be known when they are of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Devil.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. I ſhall ſhew, that howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever troubleſom and afflicting they are, they do not affect nor endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger our main State.</p>
               <p n="5">V. and Laſtly, I ſhall endeavour to preſcribe the regulation of them.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:53603:59"/> I. IT muſt be owned there is ſome difficulty in the enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into the riſe and origine of theſe horrid Thoughts, and 'tis hard to know many times whether they are the genuine Iſſue of our own corrupt Nature, or ſpurious Brats falſly father'd on us by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. For he can inject as much and more than our Corruptions can ſuggeſt, and yet poſſihly, on the other hand, they are able of themſelves, to carry us on to thoſe exceſſes that look <hi>diabolical,</hi> and when they joyn hand in hand, 'tis hard to know whether of the two firſt made the Motions or proves the abler Solicitor of their common cauſe of Sin: <hi>Out of the Heart,</hi> ſays our Saviour, <hi>proceed evil Thoughts, Murders, Adulteries,</hi> &amp;c. there they are <hi>conceived,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>begets</hi> them. And St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Romans, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 24.</note> ſome of thoſe black Crimes, for which he brands the heathen World, into <hi>the Luſts of their own Hearts,</hi> and yet at the ſame time
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53603:60"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to underſtand, that <hi>the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince of the power of the Air wrought in all ſuch Children of Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience</hi> And indeed as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. 2.</note> of divine and humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence in the progreſs of true Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety is very plain, and legible, in the Scriptures, ſo as that we are ſaid, for inſtance, to <hi>be waſhed and ſanctified by the Spirit of God,</hi> and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 11.</note> yet are required <hi>to cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the Fleſh and Spirit:</hi> So are the ſame ſins in <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 1.</note> different places charged upon the Devil, and our own Hearts too. As, <hi>David's</hi> numbring the people <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 1. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> is aſcribed to Satan, and yet the King takes it to himſelf: Juſt as it is ſaid of <hi>Ananias lying to the holy Ghoſt,</hi> that <hi>Satan</hi> put him on it, and yet that he <hi>conceived it in his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 5. 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>NOW tho it be ſomwhat diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, as we have ſeen, to know the true Parent of theſe hideous Thoughts we ſpeak of. yet,</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:53603:60"/> II. IT is of no ſmall uſe and concernment to meet with ſome ſatisfaction in the Matter; for the ſad Experience, I believe, of many, eſpecially hypocondraick Perſons, tells us, (the darkneſs of whoſe humor is beſt fitted to receive ſuch black Impreſſions,) how apt the grand Enemy of our peace is to throw theſe <hi>fiery Darts</hi> into our Hearts, and then to accuſe us of their burning within us, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a rape upon our Spirits and then lay the Child at our Doors, whereby he many times creates ſuch infinite Diſquiet of Thought, Horror of Conſcience, and Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all the Powers and Faculties of tendor Minds, that they are apt to look upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as rejected of God, deliver'd up to Satan, and in ſuch a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and forlorn Condition, that the violent hand perhaps is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thought of to put a Period to the comfortleſs and wretched Life; and therefore, I ſay, it may be of excellent Uſe, on this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="401" facs="tcp:53603:61"/> for the Support and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of theſe unhappy Perſons, to point out ſuch criterious and characteriſties, whereby <hi>the buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Satan,</hi> as we render it, <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 7.</note> may be in ſome meaſure diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the genuine productions of our own Minds, and thoſe gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally aſſign'd by Divines are ſuch as follow.</p>
               <p n="1">I. THEY are the Devil's Thoughts, not ours, when the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of them ſurpaſſes the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our natural Corruption: for Nature her ſelf, unleſs turn'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Diabolical, ſhrinks, and gives back at thoſe outragiouſly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Motions, that paſs now and then in ſome Men's Minds, and there to be ſure they are the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Devil upon them, to Vex, Diſquiet, and Confuſe their Spirits, tho he chance to prove unable to prevail with them. An evil Heart, 'tis true, may through its own inherent Wickedneſs, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure up thoſe frightful Spectres of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53603:61"/> Thoughts, that would ſcare and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze other Perſons, but that it ſhould be able, of it ſelf, to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it ſelf, to fill the mind with Horror, to ſtartle its own Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and go directly contrary to its own Affections, Inclinations, and Reluctancies, borders too much upon a contradiction to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. No Man, for inſtance, of himſelf, can be ſtudious of Life, and yet at the ſame time enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Thoughts of turning <hi>felo de ſe.</hi> The Suggeſtions of this kind that derive purely from our own Hearts, are always more or leſs agreeable to Nature, pleaſing to our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and fall in with our own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations.</p>
               <p n="2">II. THE injections of the Devil are diſcernable from the producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our own Hearts, by the <hi>Manner</hi> of their aſſailing us. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature proceeds orderly and deliberately with us, tampers and argues with our Thoughts, and through the deceitfulneſs of Sin,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53603:62"/> gradually gets ground upon us, till by ſteps and ſucceſſive ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances it compleats its intended Victory: For our own Luſts do not force, but <hi>draw us away,</hi> whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle us on, and entice us. But 'tis <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 14.</note> otherwiſe with Satanical Injections of this horrid Kind, they are a ſort of <hi>motus in inſtanti,</hi> dart and break in upon our Thoughts, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever otherwiſe imployed and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, without any previous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation of their approaches, the Devil in theſe caſes ſends no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers before him to prepare his way, but forces his paſſage on a ſuddain, ſhoots like that Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to which our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares his Fall, into our Minds, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 18.</note> Hell takes our Heaven by Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
               <p>AND as Thoughrs of this kind are thus ſuddain in their firſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacques upon us, ſo are they obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved generally to be very pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and obſtinate in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of them, which is a</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:53603:62"/> III. INDICATION that they proceed from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for tis highly agreeable to the innate ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of his temper, inceſſantly to alarm the Fort of our Souls with perplexities and anxieties of mind about his injections, even then when he ſees he is unable to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it. The</p>
               <p n="4">IV. AND laſt ſign of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Author of theſe Thoughts within us, is from the effects that generally attend them. Our own Thoughts being the natural <hi>iſſue</hi> of our own hearts do not ſcare nor affright us, nor are follow'd with any extraordinary perturbation of Mind and Spirit, and therefore when Men meet with ſuch Thoughts, as are accompanied with an horror and dread upon their Spirits, with confuſion of mind, aſtoniſhment of its powers, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with equal agonies and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions of Body, there to be ſure the Devil is the ſole operator. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable whereunto is that obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:53603:63"/> of antiquity, that they were falſe Prophets, and of Diabolical inſpiration, who were acted in a confuſed, perplexed, and diſtracted manner; the principal Teſt this whereby the Catholick Chriſtians were wont to diſtinguiſh an Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtic Montaniſt from a Divinely inſpired Prophet, as may be ſeen in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> where we find <hi>Miltiades,</hi> an Eccleſiaſtic Author writing a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 5 <hi>ch.</hi> 16. 17.</note> whole tract upon this ſubject, and <hi>Aſterius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus</hi> challenging them all to produce him one ſingle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Prophet, under either Old or New Teſtament, acted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their dark and impetuous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. For the Devil dealt violently with his Enthuſiaſts, confuſed and oppreſs'd their underſtandings, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted and convuls'd their bodily Organs, and in ſhort, put them, like the unhappy Perſons we at preſent ſpeak of, into moſt terrible agonies of Soul and Body. <hi>Pythia</hi> her ſelf never mounted the Tripos but with horror, where ſhe fomed, raved, and tore her hair, like a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53603:63"/> drunken or a frantic perſon, whilſt the Prophetick fit laſted on her: and this I was the more willing, by the by, to take notice of, becauſe the darkneſs of Mind, and violent agitations of Body, obſervable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong'ſt a company of poor beſotted, if not ſometimes poſſeſſed Sectaries amongſt our ſelves, agree ſo exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the deſcriptions antiquity has left us of thoſe Children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience the Devil wrought in then, that one may very well be tempted to conclude he repeats the experiment now and then upon theſe Men too.</p>
               <p>COME we now in the Fourth place to conſider how far theſe hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and amazing Thoughts affect our main ſtate, and touch our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; an argument ſo much the more neceſſary by how much 'tis an undoubted ſtratagem of the Devil to urge the incurſion of ſuch Thoughts upon theſe unhappy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as cauſe of deſpair and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argument of their reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:53603:64"/> and here is to be obſerved.</p>
               <p n="1">1. THAT it is not altogether in our power to govern our Thoughts, they are not abſolutely ſubject to our dominion, for the Heart of Man is as it were an high Road, through which Paſſengers both good and bad will take their way without asking leave of us; or, if you will take it under the notion of a publick Houſe, which is open to all Comers, not only to the ſober, but to lewd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd company, whoſe wild roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, curſes, and huzzas will ſtrike our Ears and we cannot help it. For we can no more prevent our <hi>ſimple apprehenſions</hi> of things, than a ſound and open eye can prevent its ſeeing, and the one is no more polluted by a viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous object than the other, and therefore to be ſure God will never condemn us for what we cannot help nor hinder, For</p>
               <p n="2">2. IT can never be Sin to us,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53603:64"/> becauſe unavoidable to be ſubject to the inroads of theſe black blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Thoughts upon our minds, no more than 'tis ſin in us to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the aſſaults of any other <hi>Temptation.</hi> What worſe is a ſober Perſon for being tempted onely to exceſs of drinking, or a chaſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to incontinence? Our Lord himſelf was <hi>tempted</hi> to commit the moſt groſs and abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and yet notwithſtanding that, was as free from ſin in his Thoughts, as from guile in his Mouth, becauſe he reſiſted the Temptation, and baffled the Tempter: We ſin on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then when we baſely give way and comply with him. The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> excuſed a Virgin that was forced in the Field (far from hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>for as when a Man riſeth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 22. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>againſt his Neighbour and ſlayeth him, even ſo is this Matter.</hi> So when the Devil commits a <hi>Rape</hi> upon our Souls by Atheiſtical, Blaſphemous, or any other Horrid Injections, if we cry out for help, abhor the baſe Suggeſtions in our
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53603:65"/> Judgment, our Will, and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, great is our Victory, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall be our Crown and Glory; guilt is our Portion only then when we embrace the bold Raviſher of our Hearts, and kiſs and hug the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of ſo monſtrous a Coaction. He were highly criminal who in a beſieg'd Town ſhould willfully ſet his own houſe on fire, but a Man certainly is not reſponſible for the fire balls and bombs that are thrown in by the Enemy, all he can and conſequently, is bound to do, is to uſe his beſt Diligence to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the fire enkindled by them; and thus it is with theſe Thoughts we ſpeak of, if we make them out of the amunition of our own hearts we are accountable for them; but if the Devil, who lays ſiege to us, throw them in, we are no farther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, then to take the beſt care we can to put them out, to ſuppreſs and hinder their ſpreading: For, <hi>that which is from within</hi> only <hi>defiles a Man,</hi> not that which is thrown in from without; if we are purely paſſive
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53603:65"/> in the matter and joyn not with the Devil's Suggeſtions, ſo long they are his Thoughts, let him look to them, they are none of ours, we have nothing to do with them.</p>
               <p n="3">III. IT would be conſidered that theſe frightful Thoughts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive many times more from an ill habit of Body than of Mind, more from poor Blood and a bad Spleen than from indiſpoſition of Soul and falſneſs of Heart. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly,</hi> whether Natural, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by Sickneſs, Loſſes, Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and ſuch Perſons are moſt infeſted with theſe horrid Thoughts) is of it ſelf apt to fill Mens heads with infinite Crotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets, the blackeſt Conceits, and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Surmiſes, it creates the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Apparitions, Mormoes, and Spectres, and then inclines the poor deluded Man to take them for Realities. Whilſt; alas! his malady is generally better cured by good Air, wholſom Diet, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53603:66"/> Chalybeats, then by all the reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of Divinity: And then what reaſon has a Man to be troubled in Mind, or dejected in Spirit, more for this than any other Diſtemper, why is poor Blood and a melancholy Diſpoſition a ſurer mark of the divine Diſpleaſure, than the burnings of a Feaver, or the ſhiverings of an Ague?</p>
               <p n="4">IV. IT may be added for the ſupport and encouragement of theſe dejected Spirits, that their malady is rarely incident, but to religious Diſpoſitions, and pious Minds, that live under tender Senſe of their Duty, and an awful dread of the divine Diſpleaſure. Were they in thoſe bonds of Iniquity, and that ſtate of Reprobation they fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure to themſelves they would never be ſo happy as to experiment any of theſe ſpiritual conflicts in their boſoms. <hi>Non timeo hos pingues,</hi> ſaid <hi>Caeſar</hi> of <hi>Dolobella,</hi> and his roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Crew, but ſober <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> ſtuck in his Stomach; the Devil
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53603:66"/> like him, never troubles his head with your ſupine unwary Sinners, who are amuſing their heads with a thouſand wicked projects that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the intereſts of his Kingdom, for he might chance to jog them out of their ſleep of ſin, and awaken them to repentance, and ſo out-wit himſelf, ſhould he fright them by theſe terrible injections: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if <hi>Ephraim is joyned to Idols,</hi> if <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 17.</note> Men are deeply ingaged in notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſins, he too ſays, like God, <hi>let him alone.</hi> For why ſhould the Prince of darkneſs be thought ſo weak a States-man as to make war upon thoſe who have already ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his government, and ſworn homage to him? But then he uſes all the black art of his infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Suggeſtions to ſtop, and vex, or diſquiet the Religious Man in his holy courſe. 'Twas righteous <hi>Job</hi> that he would fain have prevail'd with to <hi>curſe God to his face;</hi> and 'twas the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> that was
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 1. 11. &amp; 2. 5.</note> tempted by him to that horrid blaſphemy of renouncing the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53603:67"/> of the great God, and ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting him in his ſtead. So that, upon the whole, Temptations of this nature being rather an argument of a pious than irreligious temper, ought, in juſt conſtruction to be ſo far from Miniſtring ſorrow, that they may afford even matter of comfort and rejoycing to thoſe that are exerciſed therein.</p>
               <p n="5">V. AND Laſtly, Tho it muſt be confeſt that theſe black injecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, may be ſometimes, like other judgments, the Chaſtiſement of our ſins, as of our carnal ſecurity for inſtance, of neglect of our Thoughts, grieving the holy Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they are even then only the <hi>evil of puniſhment,</hi> as any other infliction may be, not of ſin to us, unleſs we like, comply with, and approve them; and when they have once gained the deſign, for which our heavenly Father ſent them on his Children, as ſuppoſe the awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to a more through Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance than they have yet arriv'd
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:53603:67"/> at, taking off their inclinations to the enjoyments of this preſent Life, teaching them a more perfect Recumbency upon God, abating their Pride, leaſt they ſhould be, with St. <hi>Paul, above meaſure exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7.</note> &amp;c. then he takes off his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting hand, reſtrains the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, quiets the mind, and ſpeaks Peace to his People.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p>THUS much of the ſecond part of our Subject, the Defects, Failures, and Infirmities incident to our Thoughts. We are now arriv'd at the third and laſt, which is to preſcribe ſome rules for the Government and Manage of them. And thus I will endeavour to do.</p>
               <p n="1">I. WITH Relation particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to theſe horrid Thoughts we have juſt now treated of.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:53603:68"/> II. WITH Relation to the ſinful infirmities of our Thoughts in religious Duties.</p>
               <p n="3">III. AND Laſtly, I ſhall lay down ſuch Rules as concern the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of our Thoughts in general.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, how we are to behave our ſelves with particular relation to theſe horrid Thoughts we have juſt now treated of. And,</p>
               <p n="1">1. THERE is no doubt to be made, but that Prayer, which is ſo proper a means to the attainment of every good and perfect Gift, and ſo powerful an Amulet againſt all the Evils we labour under, will be of ſpecial Uſe in the caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, <hi>Is any among you afflicted, ſays St.</hi> James, <hi>let him pray,</hi> and what greater affliction, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, more preſſing occaſion to Prayer than thoſe Perplexities of Mind we ſpeak of; for when can it be more opportune to call in
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53603:68"/> the Aid of Heaven, than when we are thus immediately aſſaulted by Hell? What fitter to quench theſe <hi>fiery Darts of the</hi> Wicked than the <hi>Shield of Faith</hi> in God expreſs'd <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 16.</note> by our importunate Applications to him for Relief? For then muſt it be more eſpecially acceptable to God, to teſtifie an entire Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on, and Confidence in him, when he ſeems moſt of all to hide his Face from us in Diſpleaſure. For if we thus pour out our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications before him, hungring and thirſting after the Aſſiſtances of his Spirit, and the Teſtimony of our Conſciences, to ſupport us in theſe ſpiritual Conflicts, he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and therefore no doubt but in his own good time, he will ſhine upon us with the Light of his Countenance, and yeild us Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment: Will put his hook in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Noſe, and his bridle into the Lips of the Tempter, turn him back, by the way by which he came, and give Eaſe to thoſe who have ſuffered ſo much in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53603:69"/> for fear only of having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him.</p>
               <p n="2">II. ANOTHER proper reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in this caſe, is to avoid idleneſs and ſolitary retirements; it muſt indeed be own'd, in my opinion, that Solitude is a mighty help to elevation of Mind, application of Thought, recollection of Spirit, and conſequently to true private Devotion; which might be the Reaſon, I preſume, why our Lord himſelf, on this occaſion, added ſomtimes even the darkneſs of the Night, to the retirement of the Mountains. But yet, in this caſe, when the mind, left to it ſelf is apt continually to dwell upon one's own ſuppoſed deſperate Condition, and be perpetually haunted with the Ghoſts it has conjur'd up, tis far more adviſeable to repair to the City than to the Deſart, and to chuſe Company before a Retreat: The one will help to lay the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Spirit, the other as certainly improves its Terrors. If one fall
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53603:69"/> in Society, another may lift him up again, but in Privacy, a Man muſt ſtand upon his own bottom; and be in ſome meaſure ſelf ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to encounter with the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that in circumſtances moſt advantagious to his Deſign upon us; for the temptations of Solitude are, I verily believe, more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than thoſe to be met with upon the ſtage of Action, becauſe it lays us more eſpecially open to the aſſaults of the Tempter, for which reaſon 'tis rationally preſumed he made choice of the Wilderneſs, when he encountred with our Lord and Saviour; and both Reaſon, and the experience of ſeveral, of <hi>Ignatius</hi> particularly, that famous Founder of the Jeſuit's Order, and eminent Inſtance of the Truth, aſſures us, that they who give themſelves much up to Solitude, are infinitely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to Satanical Illuſions: If therefore we would divert and break the force of theſe frightful Thoughts and Suggeſtions, we would do well to keep our Minds
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53603:70"/> imployed, either in innocent and agreeable Converſation, or when out of that, in our own and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Imployments; for idleneſs is a ſort of Solitude of the Mind, even in places of the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and gives the Devil as great an Advantage againſt us, as the other Solitude of the Deſert or the Cloiſter.</p>
               <p n="3">III. 'TIS adviſed by Divines in theſe caſes, rather to ſlight than to ſtruggle and conteſt with the Temptor; not to argue the caſe or enter into parley with him about one's Condition, (for the conflict will gall and chafe our Minds the more) but, as far as we are able, to let his Helliſh Injections go as they come, and be no more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for his blaſpheming within us, than for the Curſes and Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of any other lewd Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that we cannot get rid of. For Oppoſition do's but perpetuate the Fray, and make the Battle the hotter: A wild Beaſt, if you violently ſtop
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53603:70"/> its Paſſage, may chance to run o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you; let it alone, t'will go the gentlier by you: The way then in this caſe is, not to <hi>reſist the Devil,</hi> otherwiſe than by Prayer, but to let him ſpend his Fury, and bear his Shocks with a ſevere Contempt of them, with a reſolv'd firmneſs of Mind, and ſedateneſs of Temper, till his force diſſipates and waſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. AND Laſtly, a conſtant proſecution of one's Duty, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever irkſom and uncomfortable it may appear, will certainly in time give the Mind Eaſe, and ſet it at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from theſe Helliſh Thoughts: The Clouds that darken the Mind now will by perſeverance in Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be ſucceeded by a perfect Day, a Day of Glory and eternal Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. For God will judge no Man for what he cannot help nor hinder, but will certainly reward him who do's him the beſt Service he is able, and is grieved only he can do him no better. For 'tis true in this caſe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53603:71"/> too, that if there be <hi>a willing Mind it is accepted according to what a Man has, and not according to what he has not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>PROCEED we now to ſuch Conſiderations as may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to govern, and fix our Thoughts during our attendance upon religious Duties.</p>
               <p>AND here we cannot more profitably commence this important Work, than by the ſame meaſure we at firſt preſcribed on the laſt part of this Subject; that is, by addreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God for his Aid and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in the Matter, that not onely the <hi>Words of our Mouth, but the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations if our Heart</hi> (eſpecially in our immediate approaches to Him) may be <hi>always acceptable in the ſight of the Lord our God and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</hi> For Prayer it ſelf will faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate that application of Mind which
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53603:71"/> is neceſſary to a due performance of it, in as much as it purifies the Heart, ſublimates the Spirit, and exalts it above its natural Pitch and Level: For by often returning to God, and carefully renewing our commerce with Heaven, we ſhake off our criminal Diſpoſitions; and what was at firſt irkſom and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſomneſs to the fleſh becomes at length an eaſie and a pleaſurable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe. He will never be able to arrive to any tolerable degree of Perfection in any Attainment, whoſe deſires do not firſt carry him on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it with ſome Eagerneſs and Impatience; and Prayer is nothing but putting our deſires into Suit. He is certainly a very temerarious Perſon, who commences any Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakeing, without invokeing firſt the divine Favour and Aſſiſtance: The only proper Foundation Stone whereon to build our hopes of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in any of our Enterpriſes, and judged as ſuch even by the Heathen World it ſelf, who generally com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd their Works with appreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53603:72"/> of good Succeſs from the great Author of it. <hi>Ceſar,</hi> being to enter the Senate, ſacrificed firſt, and Prayer among them was a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Attendance upon that Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, and <hi>Appian</hi> particularly ſpeaks of that Act, not as of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, but as of a cuſtomary thing. And if this piece of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage be ſo highly our Duty in enterpriſing things that do not, I may ſay, ſo nearly regard him, how much more will it be ſo in our endeavours to attain that grace which flows directly from him, immediately concerns his Honour and is terminated in him, as its fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and onely proper Object?</p>
               <p>II. ANOTHER proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for the government of our Thoughts in religious Duties, is to qualifie and prepare our Hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand for the performance: To diſcharge all Thoughts of the World for that time from their attendance, to require them to ſtand by, to <hi>carry here or there, whilst we go and</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:53603:72"/> 
                  <hi>Pray yonder.</hi> 'Tis true indeed that the <hi>Loins of a Mind,</hi> throughly principled with the Love and Fear of the divine Majeſty, are always <hi>ready girt about</hi> for the Sacrifice, ſuch Perſons liveing under a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſenſe and practice of it, but we addreſs not here to the <hi>whole,</hi> who have no need of a ſpiritual Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, but to thoſe who are <hi>ſick</hi> of their Duty; who come to it with ten thouſand foreign and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper Ideas; with the Images of an Eſtate, a Purchaſe, a Family, a Trade, a Ball, a Conſort of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or perhaps laſt nights De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch about them: To theſe one would preſcribe ſome preparatory Phyſick, ſome ſequeſtring of the Mind from theſe ingageing Objects before they enter upon converſing with God, and correſponding with Heaven, leaſt the Thoughts that poſſeſs'd them this hour or this day, keep their haunt the next, and mar the performance. We are not wont to ruſh into the preſence of a Prince without premeditation,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53603:73"/> and ſome previous care of our Mien and Deportment, and how comes it then to paſs that we dare preſume to addreſs the Living God ſo familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo rudely. <hi>Before thou Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt,</hi> ſays the wiſe Son of <hi>Syrach, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf and be not as one that tempteth the Lord. i. e.</hi> I conceive, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſticus.</hi> 18. 23.</note> to be angry with thee, and to curſe rather then to bleſs thee, Twas one of the <hi>good things</hi> found in <hi>Jehoſhaphat, that he had prepared his Heart to ſeek God:</hi> And no Man <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 3.</note> pretends to good Muſick, before he has put his Inſtrument in tune; when <hi>our Hearts are fixed,</hi> O God, when <hi>our Hearts are fixed,</hi> then ſhall we beſt <hi>ſing and give Praiſe.</hi> Now by preparation here I do not mean thoſe ſuccinct Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we are wont to make to God upon our entering on his Service in houſes ſet a part to that propoſe, but the revolving in our Minds ſuch previous reflections as theſe. are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. THE Weight and Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53603:73"/> of the duty we are about, which is the onely proper Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyancer of the divine Bleſſings, and that by divine Appointment, and is of no leſs conſequence to us than the Supply of our wants both Spiritual and Temporal, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of this Life, and of that which is to come; tis, in a word, a tranſaction whereon depends the concern of Life and Death, and what is more, of Eternal Life, and Eternal Death; and will a Man ſlubber over ſuch a Buſineſs as this, will he plead his Cauſe ſo ſupinely as if he were bribed againſt himſelf, when ſo vaſt an Eſtate as the everlaſting Inheritance, depends upon the Iſſue of the Tryal? <hi>Moſes</hi> exhorts the Jews to hearken unto the Words of the Law, becauſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32 40.</note> ſays he, <hi>it is your Life.</hi> Prayers and Praiſes are the <hi>ſpiritual Life</hi> of a Chriſtian, and therefore when any forreign Thoughts aſſail it, either by force or fraud, we muſt take up <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> anſwer to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>I am doing a great Work ſo that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nebem:</hi> 6. 3.</note>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:53603:74"/> 
                  <hi>I cannot come down, why ſhould the work ceaſe whilſt I leave it and come down to you.</hi> A</p>
               <p n="2">2. PREPARATORY will be beſt placed upon the dread Majeſty of him we addreſs to, and his more immediate Preſence in places ſet apart for his Service; for God himſelf alledgeth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Malac.</hi> 1. 14.</note> of his Majeſty to caution Men againſt offering him any mean and contemptible Sacrifices: <hi>Curſed be the Deceiver,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which hath in his flock a Male, and voweth and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing: For I am a Great King, ſays the Lord of Hoſts, and my Name is dreadful among the Heathen;</hi> and the wiſe Man urgeth the diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the great Creator and his Creatures, as an argument of that Sobriety and exactneſs of Utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Affection that becomes his Preſence: <hi>Be not raſh with thy mouth,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and let not thine heart be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to utter any thing before God: for God is in Heaven, and thou upon earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:53603:74"/>
               <p> AY, 'tis certainly the want of a due conſideration of the terrible name of the great and living God, who is infinitely exalted above our moſt elevated Conceptions of him, that makes us ſo often preſent him with the Sacrifice of Fools, that <hi>Excors Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium,</hi> which the Heathen World look'd upon as ſo prodigious a thing. It requires indeed a genious, wide, and Philoſophical, the portion of but a few, to take in a full draught of Contemplation of the Great and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Being; and tho it muſt be own'd, that the moſt refined Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city cannot now behold him as he is, ſhining in his full Orb of Glory (for the Contemplation of his Eſſence is an Abyſs, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately devours and ſwallows up a dark and broken Underſtanding, it being a ſort of endeavour to look God in the Face, which no Man can do and Live) yet he has not leſt us without witneſſes of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in the convulſion of the Mountain, and the Agony of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at the promulgation of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53603:75"/> Law, in the loſty, but yet infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inadequate Deſcriptions that the Prophets give of him: In his works, of <hi>ſpreading out the Heavens, and treading upon the waves of the Sea,</hi> &amp;c. In thoſe frightful and amazing Accounts the Scripture give us, of the tranſactions of the laſt Day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And certainly did we but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to poſſeſs our Souls with tolerable Conceptions, of this great and dreadful Being, from theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Notices we have of him; we could not but be induced to take ſome tolerable care, how and what we ſay, when we are ſpeaking unto God, for the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the ten thouſand times ten thouſand that ſtand before him, do not more truly miniſter in his Preſence, than we do in our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to Him. And Oh! that we had but a glimps of him that is Inviſible, that the God of Heaven would but irradiate our dark ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, with ſome beam of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, with what Reverence, what Fear and Trembling, ſhould we come
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53603:75"/> before him? And this more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, in places conſecrate and ſet apart for the payment of our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to him, where he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes his more immediate and more ſpecial Preſence. Not indeed after any groſs and local manner, as the Gentiles conceiv'd of their fictitious Deities in their Temples, in which ſenſe it is ſaid of the <hi>moſt High</hi> that <hi>he dwelleth not in Temples</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>made with hands;</hi> but by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue of his Angels, which give their more immediate Attendance there, as in their Maſters houſe, by his Word and Sacraments, and by his peculiar readineſs to hear, and bleſs thoſe that devoutly call <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20 24.</note> upon his Name there; for which reaſon, as one well obſerves, the Tabernacle of the Lord was call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the Tabernacle of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> not of Mens meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as is commonly ſuppos'd, when we tranſlate it, <hi>Tabernacle of the Congregation;</hi> but of God's meeting there with Men, his poor humble Supplican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s? For ſo he <note place="margin">
                     <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mb.</hi> 17 4.</note>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:53603:76"/> himſelf gives the reaſon of the Name: <hi>And thou ſhalt lay them up</hi> ſays God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſpeaking of the Rods of the Tribes, <hi>in the Tabernacle of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezod.</hi> 25. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Congregation, before the Teſtimony; where I will meet with you. And there I will meet with thee and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with thee.</hi> And what elſe can be the true and unſtrained meaning of that Paſſage of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's in the Goſpel, where he promiſes, that where <hi>two or three are gathered together in his Name, he is there in the midſt of them?</hi> For, whatever may be particularly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Temple, a greater than <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſal.</hi> 85. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> is here, even God wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in his holy Places; ſure theſe are no other than the Houſes of God, theſe are the Gates of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p>AND therefore we would do well to take care how we make <hi>Iniquity, even the ſolemn Meeting;</hi> by affronting God with our lip Services, and that ſo <hi>immediately to his Face;</hi> For can any any Man
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53603:76"/> in his wits but think, that the great God, to whom the profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt homage of the Soul is due, is much more affronted than he is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, by the dull ſpiritleſs mutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a few <hi>Pater noſters,</hi> or any other Prayers, by the bare telling over, as the manner of ſome is, and ſtring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Petitions? We durſt not thus mock our Prince to his Face, we would hardly do it to our Equals, and whence then is it, but through want of preparing our Hearts with due Conceptions of his Awful and Majeſtick Preſence in his own Houſe, that we make thus bold with our Maker?</p>
               <p n="3">3. IT might be a proper pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory reflection to conſider the Fruits and Conſequences of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching God in ſo careleſs and ſo incogitant a Manner. I ſhall not go about to ſhew at large, how ſevere God has formerly been upon all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and irregularities committed about holy Things and Duties, as in the Caſe of <hi>Aarons</hi> Sons, of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah;</hi> of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 10. 2. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:53603:77"/> the Bethſhemites; and of the Church <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 19. 1 <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi> 11. 30.</note> of <hi>Corinth;</hi> nor how he threatn'd that for this very thing; becauſe his People <hi>drew near to him with their Lips, but had removed their Heart far from him, he would therefore</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>proceed to do a marvellous Work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, even a marvellous Work and a Wonder:</hi> Which was no leſs than to <hi>confound the wiſdom of the wiſe, and the underſtanding of the prudent Men</hi> amongſt them; I ſhall not, I ſay, inſiſt on theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations now, becauſe it has ſeem'd good to the infinite Wiſdom, to alter the nature of his Inflictions, and for neglects of this kind eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to change them from tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral into ſpiritual, which, tho they do not ſo immediately affect the Body as the others did; yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the Soul and take away the ſpiritual Life of a Chriſtian. For tho, he do's not now ſmite Men with Death, for their unſanctified Approaches to him, yet he ſmites them with <hi>Deadneſs,</hi> with Coldneſs and Indifferency in the cauſe of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53603:77"/> Religion, ſuffers them to grow liſtleſs, reaſty, and awkard at their Devotions, and ten to one to lapſe at long run into open Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs. For we certainly loſe ground by every ſpiritleſs Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er we advance, grow from bad to worſe, from worſe to ſtark nought, and <hi>paſt feeling.</hi> For every ſuch formal performance grieves the Spirit, cloggs the Conſcience, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens the Heart, and gives the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil an occaſion to draw us off from our Neutrality, and to make us at laſt declare for his Party; whence it is not improbable, that, when we have once contracted ſuch a vitious habit and craſis of Soul in Devotion, he himſelf many times ſends us to our Prayers, adding that he may add to our Diſeaſe, and turn the beſt Antidote we have againſt him into ſo much ſtronger Poiſon to our ſelves. And therefore we would do well to ſeaſon and prepare our Hearts beforehand, with theſe, and the like Conſiderations, that by a juſt Reſlection upon the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:53603:78"/> of the Duty, the Supream Majeſty to whom we pay it, and the fatal Conſequences of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functory Performance of it, we may <hi>attend upon the Lord without Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>III. ANOTHER proper means, to fix our Thoughts in the Service of God, is to <hi>Love</hi> him with all our Hearts, with all the Powers, and Capacities of our Souls; did we <hi>Delight</hi> to have our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with Him, our Hearts would keep our Minds cloſe to their Work, and not ſuffer them to loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or to ramble; for our Affections have an immediate Influence upon our Thoughts, and our Hearts ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſets our Mind the Theme of its Contemplations; Love par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly is a commanding and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Paſſion, that bids us go, and and we go; come, and we come; do this, and we do it, a paſſion that ingroſſes all our Powers, binds us faſt to, and runs our Thoughts ſo deep into its Object, that we have
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:53603:78"/> neither Leiſure, nor Patience, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power, to attend to any others. <hi>O how I love thy Law!</hi> ſays holy <hi>David,</hi> and then it follows, both in him, and in the nature of the things, <hi>it is my Meditation all the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 97.</note> 
                  <hi>Day;</hi> and the firſt part of his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a good Man is, that <hi>his Delight is in the Law of the Lord;</hi> and the ſecond is the natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of the firſt, that <hi>in his Law doth he meditate Day and Night.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1. 2.</note> For a Man cannot but pore and muſe on the thing he delights in; and therefore were our Hearts ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with the Love of God, from juſt and retired Reflections upon the benefits of Creation, Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Redemption, and the Glory that hereafter ſhall be Revealed, did we but kindle this holy Flame in us by frequent Conſiderations of his patience, forgiveneſs, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, the Abyſs of his Love, and the great depths of his infinite beneficence: things that muſt needs render the Deity amiable and lovely to us in our Conceptions of him: all
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53603:79"/> our motions would tend Heaven wards, when once invigorated with impreſſions from that celeſtial Fire, we ſhould not be at leiſure to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Rival of God in our Thoughts, and to attend to thoſe little idle Toys and Fancies, that have the impudence to ſtep into our Cloſets, and diſtract us.</p>
               <p>IV. MEDITATION is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother proper Remedy of the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of our Thoughts in Prayer. The Hill of Meditation is indeed of difficult, but yet of noble Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, that lifts us up ſo far above our natural Level, that we look down upon the World, and all its Enjoyments, which ſo frequently interrupt our Devotions, as a very little Thing. 'Tis an heroic and abſtracted Operation of the Soul, that lets us into the very ſecrets of the Objects we Contemplate; that makes every day freſh Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, and gives us both deep and diffuſed Proſpects of things other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe inviſible: the Teleſcope of the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:53603:79"/> Mind, whereby we deſcry new Worlds, <hi>a new Heaven, and a new Earth,</hi> the <hi>Terra incognita</hi> of Nature and Grace; and ſee things at an immenſe diſtance from us: It opens to us the Scene of Paradiſe it ſelf, makes a ſort of indiſtance betwixt God and our own Souls, takes us out, or, at leaſt, makes us forget that we are Fleſh, fills our head with thoſe elevated Conceptions, and warms our Heart with thoſe Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhments of Joy, that we can feel indeed but cannot utter or expreſs them. And he who has never yet been experimentally ſenſible of this Truth, never yet rightly enjoyed either God, or himſelf, has the moſt exquiſite Pleaſure of this Life yet to come, and wants the preparato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Foretaſte of the enjoyments of the other. Meditation in a word, I mean where God is the Object, both quickens and fixes our Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which embraces not its Object but in proportion as Meditation gives it Entrance.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:53603:80"/>
               <p> V. AND Laſtly Solitude gives a mighty fixation of Thought, in private, and Religious Aſſemblies in publick Devotion; for a Retreat naturally tends to Recollection of the Spirit and Communion with God, it helps to center all the Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of our Souls upon him, and gives us more pure and perfect Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; and therefore, <hi>when thou prayeſt,</hi> ſays he, who taught us to pray, <hi>enter into thy Cloſet,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to avoid that vain Pomp and Parade, which the Phariſaic Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſo much affected, but no doubt to better the Performance, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, as much as may be, from thoſe Impreſſions of worldly Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that are wont ſo fatally to perſecute and diſtract us. Any thing that requires application of Mind carries the neceſſity of Retirement along with it: How much more that Performance, to the full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge whereof the utmoſt Stretch of our humane Capacities is ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dequate: All which is by no means to be underſtood in prejudice to the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:53603:80"/> Publick Prayers of Religious Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; where the regular Gravity and Decorum of the Worſhip, the united Zeal and Devotion of the Worſhippers, the Sacredneſs of the Word that is read, the Importance of the Duty, the Dreadfulneſs of the Place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all conſpire to wing the Devout Soul with divine Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, to fix it upon God, and give it a Solitude in the great <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>AND thus much for thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies that may be proper to cure the Diſtraction and Flatneſs of our Thoughts in Gods Service.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>WE are now arrived at the laſt diviſion of our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, which is to direct to ſuch means, as may be proper for the government of our Thoughts in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. <hi>i. e.</hi> on whatſoever Subject they are exerciſed.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:53603:81"/>
               <p> AND here not to inſiſt upon that <hi>Catholicon</hi> of Prayer we have already mentioned, that which being a Soveraign and Univerſal Remedy againſt all the Evils we labour under, muſt conſequently be of excellent Uſe againſt the exorbitancies of our Thoughts; I would adviſe, in the</p>
               <p n="1">I. PLACE, to open the Scene of the Day with good and ſavory Thoughts in the Morning: To make the ſtrength and firſt born of our Conceptions every day holy to the Lord; <hi>when I awake,</hi> ſays holy <hi>David, I am preſent with thee;</hi> God ever took place in his thoughts, and was the earlieſt Theme of his Meditations. For, <hi>in the Morning,</hi> ſays he, in another place, <hi>I will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my Prayer unto thee, and will look up;</hi> we muſt, like him, if we would with him, learn to hate vain thoughts, conſecrate our moſt ſpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſparkling Meditations to him, who <hi>giveth his beloved ſleep,</hi> and yet himſelf <hi>neither ſlumbrs nor ſleeps.</hi> For there is no doubt to be made, but
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:53603:81"/> that a Mind well ſeaſoned and tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured with good Thoughts in the Morning, will, with ordinary care, retain its Smack and Fragrancy all the day; but if we let the World or the Devil in firſt, 'tis great odds but they keep poſſeſſion all the day, come home too, and go to bed with us in the Evening.</p>
               <p n="2">II. SINCE ſo much of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Thoughts is owing to the Imagination, as we have ſeen before at large, it will be highly proper to reſtrain that extravagant Power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its due bounds, to confine it home, and not ſuffer it to run out, ramble, and gad ſo far abroad amongſt variety of Objects, that we cannot at our pleaſure call it back again; to take care however that it make not falſe Reports of things, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon our Reaſon with fictitious and Romantic exaggerations of them, to draw out our Thoughts in the dance after it, but that we learn ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly to diſtinguiſh betwixt the intrinſic value of things, and the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53603:82"/> extravagant Repreſentations of a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Imagination.</p>
               <p n="3">III. SINCE our Minds receive the Ideas and Images of moſt things originally from our Senſes; ſince it is by theſe avenues that outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects make their way to our Hearts, our Ears being, as it were, the gates by which the objects from without deſire to ſpeak with our Thoughts, and our Eyes as windows to our Minds, through which they gaze upon them: It concerns us to ſet <hi>Waiters</hi> at theſe <hi>Cinque Ports</hi> of our Senſes, to <hi>ſeize</hi> upon all contraband Goods, and ſcarch all Comers, as the Governour of a Fortreſs will take care to guard its Avenues, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Paſſengers, eſpecially ſtrange Faces, leaſt it be inſenſibly betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ſurpriſed into the hands of an Enemy, under the appearance and vizor of a Friend: not that the ſenſes are of themſelves any way criminal, for they diſcharge but their reſpective Offices, according to the Laws of their Creation: Nor that
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:53603:82"/> all, or moſt of the Images of things, they let in, are noxious and ſinful, (for what harm had the wedge of Gold or Babyloniſh Garment in them, when <hi>Achan</hi> look'd upon them, coveted, and took them; and is not the fair Face drawn, and melodious Voice tun'd by the finger of God, who can do no Evil?) But they become an occaſion of Sin by the doteing of the Heart upon them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is we muſt guard our Senſes, to deprive that of the matter of its Crimes, and let its fooliſh Fire go out for want of fuel fit to keep it in. And yet how contrary to this is the practice of the World, where our Eyes are every day expos'd to the infection of wanton Pictures, light Dreſſes, natural and artificial Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to the redneſs of the Wine when it gives its colour in the glaſs, and to a thouſand criminal Examples, and our Ears ſtand all the day open to amorous Romantic Stories, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene Jeſts, Back-bitings, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilings, and moſt times to flat and inſipid Diſcourſes, that neither mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53603:83"/> Morality, nor Grace, nor Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the Hearers, ſo that our Souls return home at night infected with the vain Air of the courſes of the day, and full charged with toys and ten thouſand Amuſemnets, which leave ſuch ſenſible Impreſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, that we are ſtill hanker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after thoſe Objects, that gave us ſo agreeable a Diverſion, our Minds become unwilling Inhabitants of their tenements of Clay, and little better perhaps than Captives taken by Satan at his Will. The <hi>Tree was pleaſant to the Eye,</hi> and then the poor Woman inveigled by her Senſe, could not forbear to take and eat of the Fruit: So that we had need go and learn what that means, <hi>touch not, taſte not, handle not;</hi> had need not gaze on a Maid, in the advice of the wiſe Son of <hi>Syrach, leaſt we fall by thoſe things that are precious in her,</hi> and our <hi>Eyes</hi> be <hi>full of Adultery;</hi> had need, in this Senſe too, <hi>take heed how we hear,</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> (in <hi>Solomons</hi> advice) <hi>from the preſence of a fooliſh Man, when we perceive not in him the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 7.</note>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:53603:83"/> 
                  <hi>lips of Knowledge,</hi> or wiſe and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Diſcourſe. Had, the Royal <hi>David,</hi> with <hi>Job, made a covenant with his Eyes,</hi> both he and <hi>Bathſheba</hi> had preſerv'd their Innocence, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> his Life; but Alas! the King kept no Life-guard there (as I may properly call it) where it ſeems it was moſt needful, and ſo the <hi>Man after God's Heart,</hi> ſuffered his own to walk, in <hi>Jobs</hi> Expreſſion, <hi>after his Eyes, his ſteps turn'd out of the Way, and he was deceiv'd by a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> And therefore if we would take one primary Step towards the government and good diſcipline of our Thoughts, we muſt, as far as we are able amidſt that variety of objects that perpetuelly ſurround us, turn away our Eyes from beholding Vanity, and our Ears from hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Folly, muſt ſhut the gates againſt the Enemies of our Peace, and not enter into parley with them, leaſt they beck and ſmile upon our Thoughts, give them good Words, call them out, and they, and our affections, that are conſequent
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:53603:84"/> upon them, tempt us to yeild and ſurrender our Innocence.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. THEREFORE, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of this, it will be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to make a right choice of the company we keep; which has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, ſo unreaſonable an Awe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the modeſty of humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in its propenſions towards Good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that like St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Perſon, in the <hi>7th.</hi> to the Romans, by reaſon of it, <hi>the good that we would, we do not.</hi> For
'tis a hardy well reſolv'd Piety, that ventures to exert in bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, <hi>but the evil which we would not, that we do:</hi> For the byas of our own propenſions natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclines us to follow criminal before good Examples. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we would effectually preſerve our Innocence, we muſt not only let no profane or lewd Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on proceed out of our own Mouths, but muſt be deaf to all that's vented by others. For, believe me, there's a ſtrange malignity in bad converſe to poyſon and infect even the beſt
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:53603:84"/> Diſpoſitions: A ſort of <hi>effluvia,</hi> as a learned Perſon of our own ſpeaks, from the Spirits of Men as well as from their Bodies; <hi>with the Clean thou ſhalt be Clean, and with the Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thou ſhalt learn Frowardneſs,</hi> for Lewdneſs has but a ſhort and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Paſſage from the Ear to the Heart. And therefore what King <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſes in relation to the angry and furious Man, that we <hi>make no friendſhip with him, leaſt we</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 23 24.</note> 
                  <hi>learn his ways, and get a ſnare to our Soul,</hi> is equally applicable to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtance of bad Acquaintance; for <hi>he that touches pitch ſhall be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therewith,</hi> ſays the Son of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach;</hi> and <hi>can a Man,</hi> ſays the wiſe King, <hi>take fire in his Boſom, and his cloaths not be burnt, can he go upon hot Coals, and his feet not be burnt?</hi> Will evil Communication let your Manners go as good as it found them? Or, is it not rather verified by the experience of every ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſerver of himſelf, that when we meet with an agreeable, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever dangerous or deſtructive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:53603:85"/> we carry it home along with us, ſuck it in, and our Thoughts chew the cud ſo long upon it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times in our moſt private Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we aſſimilate the vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nutriment into a part, as it were, of our very Compoſition. And therefore the beſt way to ſecure our Thoughts from Infection, is, to practiſe with the Adder, to ſhut our Ears againſt the voice of ſuch Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, charm they never ſo agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to our own corrupt Inclinations. <hi>To accept no Perſon against our own Soul, and not let the Reverence of any Man cauſe us to fall,</hi> but to exchange <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 4. 22.</note> the Communion of Devils for that of Saints; whoſe Examples and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutarie Diſcourſes may ſeaſon our Minds, and, as Iron ſharpens Iron, rub off the ruſt we have contracted, and give an edge to our Spirits.</p>
               <p n="5">V. AND as Men ſhould be thus choice in their company in order to the preſervation of their Thoughts, ſo likewiſe the ſame care would be had of thoſe Books, upon which they
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53603:85"/> now and then imploy their vacant hours. It will not be a vanity to affirm that no Nation in the World ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds our own for variety of good Books, publiſh'd in our own Language, and adapted to all Capacities; and yet, ſo far of late Years have we ſuckt in the French Air, that, as ſome have laboured the Introduction of their Government amongſt us, tho the moſt uneaſie and tyrannical in Chriſtendom, ſo others have as greedily imitated them in their Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and made their Vanities claſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and authentick: I mean particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly their Plays, Operas, Farces, Romances, and other ſuch like curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cobweb Work of idle Brains; in ſo much that a Man may ſay on this Occaſion, with King <hi>Solomon; the Heart of him that hath <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſeeketh Knowledge, but the mouth of Fools feeds on Fooliſhneſs.</hi> Such Fools amuſe and pleaſe themſelves with the remembrance of idle and fictitious Stories, with the amours of one Romantic Hero, and the brave imaginary Exploits of another: And
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:53603:86"/> thus the head is fill'd with Froth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Brains, and the Thoughts, <hi>Camelion-like,</hi> live on the Air, on <hi>that indeed which is not,</hi> as having no other Being but what a fruitful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, and a roving Fancy gives it. I ſay then, that for the better or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Men's Thoughts, it will be requiſite that they lay out their vacant hours to better purpoſe, particularly on thoſe infallible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of eternal Wiſdom that are able to <hi>make them wiſe unto Salvation,</hi> and endeavour to fraight their heads with Piety, and Senſe, inſtead of Fumes and Feathers. For what Men read, if it fall in with their own fooliſh and corrupt Inclinations, leaves laſting Impreſſions behind it, and, generally, the worſt thing that paſſes in Converſation, either with the Living or the Dead, ſticks the longeſt by us, and affords moſt food for the Thoughts to feed upon, and 'tis well, after all, if ſuch Perſons proceed yet no farther, and turn not the well told legendarie Tales that they Read, into true and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:53603:86"/> real Hiſtory by their Practice.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. THEN ſince the Vanity of Thoughts is ſo much owing to the ill Supplies they meet with, partly from idle Books, partly from as idle Converſation, it will be further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to furniſh the mind with good materials, for it to exert and deſcant on. Since the crudities of the Soul like thoſe of the Stomach proceed ſo much from thoſe ill Juices which have vitiated its tone and digeſtion; we muſt provide it better food and more wholeſom diet, to recover its taſte, its due craſſis, and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for the Soul as well as the Body is apt to participate of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of that which affords it its u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Nouriſhment. And, here we have as large a Table ſpread for our mental Repaſt, as the wonders con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in God, in Nature, and in Grace can furniſh. View the firſt of theſe in his Almighty Power, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as he ſpake the World out of Nothing, ſo he can, not only think, but return it into Nothing again:
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:53603:87"/> In his Immenſity, whereby he fills all Places, and is contained of None: In the Unity and Simplicity of his Nature, a whole without parts: In his Underſtanding to which the Truth of all things before they had a Being, was as broad noon day to him, or rather he to them, their Eſſences being all diſplayed in, and derived from his own: In his Will, the immediate Efflux or firſt Born of his Underſtanding, and yet co-evous with its Parent: View him in the Juſtice of his Judgments, in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Providence, and in his Goodneſs towards the Children of Men. <hi>Whoſo is wiſe will conſider theſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 107. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>things, and they ſhall understand the lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs of the Lord:</hi> Or look over, in the next place, the Book of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the <hi>Heaven's the work of his Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the Moon and the Stars which he hath ordained:</hi> Thoſe Immenſe <hi>fire Works,</hi> whoſe motion is as regular <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8. 3.</note> as rapid, and are but as the twilight of the everlaſting Day, and of that Light which is inacceſſible: Read him further yet in the amazing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:53603:87"/> of his Grace, when <hi>he recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled the World to himſelf in Christ,</hi> let the <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs</hi> be ever preſent to thy Mind; <hi>God manifeſt in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>the Fleſh, justified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preach'd unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World, received up into Glory.</hi> But it cannot be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that I ſhould enter into the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail of thoſe innumerous Objects that afford proper Matter for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and Improvement of our Thoughts; and therefore the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct Advice of the Apoſtle will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitely take place here: <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever are honeſt, whatſoever things are iuſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report,: If there be any Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or if there be any Praiſe think on theſe Things.</hi> For, the Truth and Reaſon of all is, the Spirit of a Man is an active reſtleſs Principle of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Motion, that will not be wholly idle, but will be doing, tho it be nothing to the purpoſe, rather than do juſt nothing at all. And
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:53603:88"/> therefore unleſs you furniſh it with good ſtuff to work upon, it will take up with that which is next at hand at all adventures; ſo that if we would <hi>bring forth good things,</hi> in our Saviours Language, we muſt, with his <hi>good Man,</hi> have a <hi>good treaſure in our Hearts: (How precious are thy Thoughts to me, O God,</hi> ſays holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, how great is the ſum of them)</hi> not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139. 17.</note> a ſmall inconſiderable Stock of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Knowledge, but a Treaſure, a good Fond, or Bank, for our Thoughts to trade with, and then we ſhall increaſe with the increaſe of God. King <hi>Solomon</hi> requiring us to bind the divine Law continually upon our Hearts, adds, that when we go <hi>it ſhall lead us: When we ſleep</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>it ſhall keep us,</hi> and when we awake it ſhall talk with us. <hi>i. e.</hi> It will entertain our Thoughts, and bear them Company, when we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or, as it's ſaid upon the ſame Occaſion, <hi>when we walk by the way,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>when we lie down, and when we riſe up:</hi> Times generally of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Retirement. But now without
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:53603:88"/> this good Society at Home, our Thoughts will certainly ſeek out for new Acquaintance; gad abroad for fellowſhip with ſome other Objects; and ten to one in their jant fall into bad Company: Aſſociate with the <hi>Luſts of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eye, or the Pride of Life;</hi> and get thoſe ill haunts that our Minds per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may never after have the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to abandon,</p>
               <p>BUT becauſe neither Nature nor Education has furniſh'd all Men with equal matter for their Thoughts, and there are different ſizes in Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding as well as in Stature, therefore</p>
               <p>VII. ONE would adviſe to a more comprehenſive Expedient for the government of Thoughts which every one is capable of uſing, and that is for Men to be diligent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious in that Calling or Station wherein Providence has placed them; to do, as the wiſe King adviſes, <hi>with all their might what their hands find to</hi>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:53603:89"/> 
                  <hi>do.</hi> For this confines the ſtream of our Thoughts to their proper Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, and hinders them from over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing their Bank; this hedges in the ramblers, and keeps them to their own Incloſure, who, if left unconfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, would, like <hi>Jeremy's</hi> wild <hi>Aſs ſnuff up the Wind,</hi> and obſerve no meaſures. God who is the Father of the Spirits of all Fleſh, knew that he had made them active reſtleſs things, and therefore to imploy and find them work, to keep them do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as they ought, when they are not immediately ingaged in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he deſign'd Men their reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Callings and Profeſſions, and ſix parts of time in ſeven for them to take up their Thoughts and imploy them, and if they are not thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged about their own Buſineſs, 'tis odds, but that like St. <hi>Paul's buſie Bodies, they wander from Houſe to Houſe,</hi> mind other Men's, and <hi>med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with many Matters;</hi> which may in time cauſe as great Combuſtions without, as they do diſorder the Head within. Let our Thoughts
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:53603:89"/> then keep within their own lines, and make no incroachments <hi>hitherto,</hi> within the circle of our own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per buſineſs and Station, let their <hi>proud waves go, and no farther.</hi> Let his Thoughts who is appointed <hi>to the Miniſtry wait on his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring,</hi> his, who is to <hi>teach, on teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. IT were adviſable for Men's better ordering their Thoughts, to make choice, as far as they can, of ſuch imployments and courſe of life, as is moſt ſuitable to their genius, and abilities of Mind, for that always ſits the eaſieſt on them, and their Thoughts more Naturally fall in with their buſineſs and abide by it; Whereas if Men's imploys lie croſs the grain of their inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, their Thoughts will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually running after ſomething elſe, at which they are not ſo awkard, or if they aſpire at things to which their ſtrength bears no proportion; <hi>matters too high for them,</hi> and above the ſphere of their activity; the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:53603:90"/> weight of the burden will render them painful and uneaſie; make them <hi>ſtagger too and fro like a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Man, and bring them to their wits end,</hi> beſides the damage they may occaſion to the publick; as <hi>Phaeton</hi> endeavouring to mount his Fathers Chariot, the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof he did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, was thereby thrown out of Heaven, and had like to have ſet the World on fire.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. NEXT to this it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ſubjoyn the advice of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to contract rather then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large our ſecular affairs, inſtead of ſpreading them wider, to reduce them to as tight and narrow a compaſs as we can, that we may the better attend to the improvement of our own Minds; an acquiſition infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely beyond the moſt pompous temporal attainment. For what are honours, riches, pleaſures, all the World, to a brave refined and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed Mind? Now multiplicity of buſineſs is a mighty obſtruction
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:53603:90"/> to this mental improvement. He that thinks of many things thinks of nothing, as he that would go ſeveral ways ſtands ſtill; it diſtracts and divides our Thoughts, like water mixt with wine, debilitates and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutes them; that River will neither be ſo deep, nor ſo ſerviceable for Trade, that is divided into a great many little channels, as that which flows altogether in its own natural bed. Thus it is with our Thoughts, if we let them out at every little chink, which the concerns of the World, make in them, they'l be but ſhallow Thoughts, and mar the improvement of our Minds. A Ray collected into a point is far more intenſe than one variouſly refracted. As God do's not love idle, ſo neither over buſie people: <hi>Martha's</hi> fault was not that ſhe was imployed in ill but in <hi>many</hi> things, which juſtled for that time the <hi>good part</hi> out of her Mind. Cares intangle and perplex the Thoughts, and too much World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſineſs limes and clings the wings of our Mind ſo faſt that it cannot take its due and natural ſlight. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:53603:91"/> of objects ever weakens and diſtracts the force of our faculties, which are ſo ſtinted in their opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they cannot with any tollerable vigor direct to more than one mark at once, and therefore if we would bear a due regard to the trueſt improvement of our Minds, and management of our Thoughts, we muſt narrow our ſecular affairs as much as we can; leſt the <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of buſineſs,</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, occaſions <hi>dreams</hi> in ſleep, make our Thoughts to be little better in the day time. And therefore in order to take off our Minds from a too greedy purſuit of ſecular concernments, that we may be thereby the better inabled to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon God and our own Souls without diſtraction, let us</p>
               <p n="10">X. IN the next place, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet before us the vanity of the World, and the emptineſs of all its injoyments. Remembring that that was the reſult of <hi>Solomon's</hi> vaſt experience in this kind. <hi>Vanity</hi> was the Motto he inſcribed on all things <hi>under the Sun:</hi> for even <hi>when he gave</hi>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:53603:91"/> 
                  <hi>his heart to know wiſdom and to know madneſs and folly, to ſeek and to ſearch out by wiſdom concerning all things that are done under Heaven,</hi> even this alſo, this noble imployment of his vaſt capacities, he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces no better than <hi>vexation of Spirit:</hi> for <hi>in much wiſdom,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is much grief, and he that increaſeth knowledge</hi> (it ſelf) <hi>do's but increaſe his ſorrow.</hi> And if this great Maſter of experience and skillful obſerver of things met with ſo very little ſatisfaction, even in the purſuit of knowledge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves the <hi>concluſion of the whole matter.</hi> as he ſpeaks, into the <hi>fearing of God and keeping his commandments,</hi> we may ſafely conclude, that there is nothing here below adequate to the large Soul of Man, worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage his affections, and ingroſs his powers, and if we can but thus wean our Thoughts from the World and its allurements, we ſhall then be at liberty to lay them out elſwhere to better purpoſe, and to our own greater and more laſting ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>NOT that what I have ſaid on
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:53603:92"/> theſe two laſt heads, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as if I would have all Men devote themſelves to Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to quit the World and their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Imployments, and meddle with no buſineſs; for I preſcribe it.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. IN the next place, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent remedy againſt evil Thoughts to avoid Idleneſs, which in common experience ever gives the Devil an advantage againſt us; when <hi>David</hi> coming from lolling on his Bed wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked idly, it ſhould ſeem, on the Roof of his Houſe, he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.</note> preſented <hi>Bathſheba</hi> to his Thoughts and ſoon prevailed with him to accept of the Proffer. For when we are the idleſt he is the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt; when we do the leaſt he do's the moſt with us: If our Minds ſleep, he'l ſow his Tares the faſter, and if we let them lie fallow, Weeds will be the natural Product of the neglected Soil. Standing Minds, like ſtanding Waters, puddle and corrupt, and become the proper E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement of Vermin.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:53603:92"/> XII. AGAIN, it will be our Wiſdom, for the better management of our Thoughts, now and then to review them, to call them together to the Muſter, and examine the ſtate and plight of our Minds, to encourage good Motions, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance Bad, and to let them know we have ſet a ſpie upon them, and that they come not there with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our Obſervation. And becauſe every Man has his blind Side, and the Sin of his Boſom, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently our Thoughts run further into ſome ſort of Objects than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we muſt take particular care, and after ſuch review ſhall be better inabled, to guard there moſt, where our Thoughts ply the moſt, where their haunts are, and the company they moſt delight in; as he who commands in chief in a Siege will place the ſtrongeſt Guard there, where the Walls or other Fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Town are the weakeſt. So, if you find that luſt, for inſtance, has ſtollen in at the Windows of your eyes, and got the greateſt aſcendant over you, watch your Thoughts
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:53603:93"/> on that ſide, for there they'l be ſure to hanker; So, again, if you obſerve your ſelf the weakeſt on the ſide of provocations, and Anger be your infirmity, take care to have your Reaſon within call, and take off your Thoughts betimes from reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and meditating revenge, for that's the ſubject they'l be ſure moſt of all to dwell on, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And thus by reveiwing our Thoughts we ſhall both acquire power, and learn how to manage them, and be able to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the Devil, who knowing our ſtrong and feeble part, better many times than we do our ſelves, always layes his train there where 'tis moſt likely to take fire, and to blow up our Hearts, the ſtrong Fort of our innocence.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. SINCE, as has been before obſerv'd, our Thoughts are generally too much at the command of our paſſions, ſo that look what ſort of affections bear the ſway in a Man's heart, that way his Thoughts will take their courſe, therefore is it highly adviſable, again, to ride
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:53603:93"/> this brutal part of us with a ſtrait rein, to raiſe and ſpiritualize our <hi>affections</hi> by <hi>ſetting them on things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</hi> and not letting them run ſo madly as they do on <hi>things that are upon the earth.</hi> For tho Thoughts give the firſt being to affections, as no Man can love or hate a thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thinks on't, yet when they are once placed upon their objects they make our Thoughts dance after them at their pleaſure. As if fear has ſeiz'd us, it calls in all our Thoughts to view the frightful object, diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders our powers, and makes the mind paint the bugbear with unjuſt dimenſions, perhaps, and unnatural colours; ſo if deſire carry us abroad amongſt variety of objects, our Thoughts muſt keep it company and lie under that infinite perplexity and diſtraction that naturally attends its extravagance, and therefore if we would command our Thoughts, we muſt firſt learn to command our paſſions.</p>
               <p n="14">XIV. HE that would have the company of good Thoughts muſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:53603:94"/> entertain them kindly, and give them a friendly reception when they come and viſit him. If you receive them coldly, and with an Air of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency, they'l be as ſhie to you in time, as you can be to them; for the Divine <hi>Spirit,</hi> the great Author of them, will not always <hi>strive</hi> with Men, but will take wing, fly away, and deſert you, for they are nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble movers, and are ſent upon an errand that is your own trueſt inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and therefore if you have not yet learnt to be wiſe to your ſelves, by cloſing with their propoſals, co-operating with them, and <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out your own Salvation,</hi> they have no Commiſſion to force or drive you on to happineſs, like <hi>an horſe or mule that have no underſtanding,</hi> but will leave you not only where, but worſe than they found you.</p>
               <p n="15">XV. SINCE few Men are of that ſtrong and athletick temper of Soul, as to be able to bear the ſhocks of adverſity, but that it generally ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles and diſcompoſes their Thoughts, and, like the deſperate puſhes of
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:53603:94"/> an enemy, breaks their ranks, and puts them in diſorder, it would be therefore of excellent and common uſe for the management of our Thoughts in thoſe exigences, to be verſt in the Theory of the Divine diſpenſations, to bring our ſelves to a recumbency upon God, and <hi>commit our cares to him who careth for us,</hi> that we may thereby maintain an evenneſs of temper amidſt the rougheſt emergencies; and enjoy a calm of mind within, amidſt the loudeſt ſtorms without.</p>
               <p n="16">XVI. AGAIN, ſince, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the immaterial and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual nature of the Soul, it is capable of being wrought upon, and affected by the body during their union; for when once link'd and wedded toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there ariſeth a mutual ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy betwixt the unequal couple, and that thence doubtleſs proceed many fooliſh, wandering, and impure co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, it would be adviſable to tame the one by the macerations of the other, to mortifie the fleſh, to <hi>keep our bodies under,</hi> and not cram
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:53603:95"/> and indulge them, till the Beaſt rides the Man, till they grow too hard for our reaſon, throw off its govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and draw even it in too, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the motions and ſolicitations of the fleſh. For the <hi>flames</hi> of luſt <hi>quench the ſpirit,</hi> as the ſcorching Sun beams put out the gentler heat of the fire. Foul weather in the lower Region ſends up nought but filthy Streams and vapours. <hi>The pure in Heart only ſhall ſee God</hi> here, as well as hereafter; and thence be furniſhed with juſt and elevated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions: for he will not accept <hi>pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Bread upon his Altar:</hi> Nor will <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 1. 7.</note> admit an unclean ſacrifice. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we would be Maſters of our own Thoughts, we muſt firſt be Maſters of our Appetites, and not pamper and indulge our Carkaſſes, but wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avoiding all exceſſes of this kind, muſt endeavour by a Subſtraction of unneceſſary fuel from the Body to let the fire thereby kindled in our Thoughts go out.</p>
               <p n="17">XVII. LASTLY, it will high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conduce to the ordering of our
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:53603:95"/> Thoughts aright, to live, as much as poſſibly we can, under this Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, that Almighty God is preſent with them, ſee's, knows, reads, and ſcans their ſubtleſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and darkeſt Intrigues, better than the Eyes and Ears of Men hear or ſee them in their fruits of Words and Actions. For lo there is not a Thought in our Heart, but <hi>he knoweth it altogether, and afar off, for I know their Imagination,</hi> ſays God, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his People, <hi>which they go about</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>even now, before I have brought them into the land which I ſwear; For He, even He only, knows all the Hearts of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>the Children of Men;</hi> and, as <hi>Job</hi> ſays, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>no Thought can be witholden from him: Hell and Deſtruction are before him,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>how much more then the Hearts of the Children of Men?</hi> For ſhall not the Almighty Artificer, who <hi>made the Heart,</hi> know all the wheels, the ſprings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd movements that are in it? Go then, and <hi>aſcend up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> in the Pſalmiſt's Rethorick on this occaſion, <hi>make thy bed in Hell, take the wings of the morning and dwell in the uttermoſt parts of the Sea,</hi> go
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:53603:96"/> whither, do what thou wilt, there's an Ear to over-hear thee, an Eye to over-look thee, and an inviſible hand to tranſcribe and regiſter the cloſeſt tranſactions of thy Mind: We find the Royal <hi>David</hi> had ſuch a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual lively Senſe of this matter on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 139.</note> him, that he tells us, <hi>when he awaked God was ever preſent with him,</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd immediately to his Mind; as thoſe objects generally do at our wakening, which moſt of all engroſs our Thoughts. And could we but learn to live under the ſame quick Apprehenſion, would we <hi>walk</hi> leſs by Senſe and more by <hi>Faith,</hi> and look through at thoſe things that lie <hi>within the Vail,</hi> it would be a mighty uſe to us in the management of this hidden and unſeen part of us. For ſince our Sins in embrio at their firſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Soul, are as loathſom in Gods Eyes, as they are in their Birth and Production ſhameful in the eyes of Men: Since the remarks of thoſe who are of like Infirmities with our ſelves are powerful enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, to the regulation of our outward Behaviour, and we ſhould
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:53603:96"/> really be in confuſion, to have any grave ſober Friend, whoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem we value, and whoſe judgment we revere, privy to all the fooliſh and unhallowed Thoughts of our Souls; how much rather ſhould the conſideration of Gods all-ſeeing Eye lay a reſtraint upon our internal Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies? For what abſurdity is this to be aſhamed of what paſſes in our Thoughts, could Men pry into thoſe receſſes, and yet to let God look on without the leaſt Emotion? What inadvertancy, or Atheiſm rather is it, to be aſhamed or afraid of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert act of wickedneſs, leaſt Men ſhould find us out, and yet at the ſame time riot in our Hearts, and debauch in our Thoughts, when God all the while ſtands by a Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctator, and if he pleas'd himſelf, a juſt Avenger of all ſuch impious Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions? Since then God certainly knows all that paſſes in our Hearts, ſees and obſerves who comes in, and who goes out, is intimate to every unclean, or otherwiſe ſinful Thought, to every unlawful Deſire, to every malicious and revengeful Wiſh; to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:53603:97"/> whatſoever, in a word, is tranſacted in that Cabinet Councel; let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after ſuch an habituated Thought of God, as may mix him, not in our actions onely, but in all the movements of our Minds: Let the conſideration of his Preſence ingage us to keep ſtrict Diſcipline there, to Order, and Govern, and Manage our Thoughts aright; as what are all open and naked in his Sight, for ſurely the Lord is with them, tho perhaps we are not aware of it.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſhut up the whole with the excellent Collect of our Church rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to this Purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALMIGHTY GOD, unto whom all Hearts be open, all Deſires known, and from whom no Secrets are hid; cleanſe the Thoughts of our Hearts by the Inſpiration of thy Holy Spirit; that we may perfectly love thee, and worthily magnifie thy Holy Name, through Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:53603:97"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
